<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The right religion, reviewed and inlarged / by L.P. Gent.</title>
            <author>L. P., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 140 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 94 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P74C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077552</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077552</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151629</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151629)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2268:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The right religion, reviewed and inlarged / by L.P. Gent.</title>
                  <author>L. P., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 175 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.LVIII. [1658]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpieces.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Newberry Library, Chicago, Illinois.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151629:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RIGHT RELIGION, <hi>Reviewed and inlarged</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>L. P.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John.</hi> 24.</bibl>
               <p>No man cometh to the Father, but by Me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezekiel.</hi> 13.</bibl>
               <p>Woe be to foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh prophets, that follow their own ſpirit; they ſee nothing but vain things, and divine lies, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The Lord: whereas the Lord hath not ſent them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at PARIS, M.DC.LVIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151629:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151629:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE CATHOLIKES OF <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe old ſaying, Truth purchaſeth hatred, is verified at this time, wherein Truth is grown ſo loathſome and hatefull, that whoſoever goes about to tell it, indangers diſpleaſure. It is ſtrange, that any can take diſtaſt at that all deſire; which is to know the truth;
<pb facs="tcp:151629:3"/>Truth being the natural plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing object of the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Nevertheleſſe ſuch is the perverſeneſs and vanity of ſome, that they deſpiſe and maligne what ought moſt of all to be cheriſht and loved: of whom it is ſaid, <hi>They prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red darkneſs before light, Joh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Having then undertaken in this ſmall Treatiſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Gods revealed Truth, I ſhould be wanting to my ſelf in ſo dangerous an enterprize, if I did make choice of any other Patronage than yours  (Renowned Catholikes) whoſe many and glorious ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings for the ſaid Truth have rankt you in the number
<pb facs="tcp:151629:3"/>of the beſt and greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors: Others hold depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Fortun, you of Grace; they ſurmount force and ſtrength common to beaſts, you, Reaſon and Will proper to men: They overcome van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh'd men, you, conquerors themſelves; their conqueſt is of others onely, yours of others and your ſelves too. In a word, all the addition that is to be made to your greatneſs is a continuance of patience and conſtancy: And this God hath in ſtore, and will give, conditionally that you ask it heartily; He that hath begun a good work in you, deſires no better than to
<pb facs="tcp:151629:4"/>perfect the ſame. What need you fear? your enemies may hurt themſelves, but want power to wrong you, unleſſe you will: Nay, their worſt is your beſt: taking away your eſtates, your good names, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaving you of your Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, your lives (thoſe <hi>bruta fulmina,</hi> which render them ſo formidable) begets you a richer and ſurer poſſeſſion, <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Eternity.</hi> All the pudder they keep in vexing you is but ſowing your ſeed for you; which undoubtedly will grow up to an hundred fold increaſe. Let them ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, cut, hew you, till they are weary; they do no more
<pb facs="tcp:151629:4"/>than carve and fit you for the walls of Heaven. And who can juſtly ſay he is a loſer, that changes for better? gets much with the loſſe of little? Take a ſerious view of the B. Saints, that paſſed, as you do, through a ſea of calamites and troubles, and are now at reſt with God; and amongſt them all you will not diſcover one complaining. The richneſſe and magnificence of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward hath ſo fully recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their forrows and loſſes, that they wonder at the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe and repining of ſome to part with; and at the greedineſſe and injuſtice of others to wreſt from, that
<pb facs="tcp:151629:5"/>which neither can long keep. For the covenant betwixt birth and death ſtands firm and inviolable; as that gives all things, this muſt return all bare and naked. This, I know, is meer folly to hardened Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines, that look not beyond the fading pleaſures of this life; but not to melting Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who believe, and are aſſured, that Heaven is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, a Gole, a Crown; which are not to be atchieved by ſitting ſtill, by leading a licentious and inordinate life, but by flying evill, overcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing temptations, doing good and vertuous acts. Take heart therefore, (brave Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons)
<pb facs="tcp:151629:5"/>and be not daunted: for your greater comfort and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, reſt aſſured that God is with you, yea, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalls the very field you fight in; and when he ſees it for your ſpirituall advantage, he will either cauſe a retreat to ſound, that you may have a time of breathing in this world; or crown you with victory, that he may have juſt cauſe to reward you in the next. Then your perſecutors will be at a ſtand, have no more to ſay to you, and your troubles will be at an end, your mourning out, your cries and ſighs ceaſe, your grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances heard and redreſſed,
<pb facs="tcp:151629:6"/>your teares dried up, the ſweat of your browes wiped away; and finding your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive gain, unſpeakeable joy will ſeize your hearts, and make you glad, that you had the grace and courage, to ſuffer for ſo good and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a God. For my part, I ſhall ever acknowledge your greatneſs, admire your glory, and from your goodneſs raiſe to my ſelf a hope, that you will dart a ray, to quicken and cheriſh theſe my indeavours, whereby you will add an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to my being.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your devoted Friend and Servant, L. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151629:6"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>OF many Religions profeſſed in this land, ſeverall Writers (men of approved integrity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found learning) have ſo clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated, that there is onely one true, and that the Roman is it; that I cannot but impute the unge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall acknowledging of the ſame to prejudice, or impatience of labor: To prejudice, in them that have read their works, and yet do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve accordingly: To impatience of labor in others, that will not beſtow the paines to turn over great vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes. The beſt remedy for that ſort of men is, to implore the Divine Goodneſs for cleane and unbiaſſ'd hearts; without which it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to behold the radiancy of Truth: For this, J have endeavoured to draw Catholike Belief into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:151629:7"/>room, as a vaſt world into a ſmall Map; to the end, that with a little travails much may be diſcovered. Jn purſuance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of J ſhew in the firſt place the end of man; in the next, the will of God, and the means which he hath appointed to attain to this end. Then I evince the weakneſs and vanity of ſuch pretences as divers make to this and other means. Laſtly the true Church appears in her right colours. And for aſ much as Truth ſhines bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by oppoſition, after the manne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of contraries, the maineſt Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Adverſaries are propoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſolved. By all which, if Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> prove to be glorifyed, and you rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> benefit, I ſhall have the return <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> deſire and wiſh, my aime being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> other than Gods Glory, and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151629:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Right Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiw'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Of happineſſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THE ſeverall knowledges of things within and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reach of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, are ſufficient. Evidences, that there is a naturall, and a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall ſtate; in both which, God is the beginning and end of all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the naturall: for who is ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151629:8"/>ſhort-ſighted, that doth not ſee that what hath been, &amp; is at this preſent exiſtent and viſible, was not alwayes ſo? That then it could not produce it ſelfe out of the void ſtate of nothing; and by conſequence that it needed an active Beginning, that never was nothing, and ever ſomething, whereby to bring nothing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence and being. And who ſo ſtupid, that doth not feele want, or ſatiety in the poſſeſſion of whatſoever is created or made? Honours expoſe as Cedars on Hills, to the boyſterous ſtorms of Envy and malice: lift up high to make the fall greater: Riches oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion dangers; beget, dropſie-like, new longings; rack the thoughts day &amp; night with care of keeping, apprehenſion of loſing. Pleaſures if they ſtay, glut: gone,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151629:8"/>leave behind them ſadneſſe and remorſe. Health is beſet on all ſides; contraries lying perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally beating, and knocking at the four humours, to let in diſtemper. Strength, be it never ſo vigorous, is at length weakened, and jaded by motion and labour. Beauty fadeth away; Age (the canker-worme of mortality) gnawerh her ſleek ſmoothneſs into roughneſſe and wrinkles. The faculties and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites live in dependence of action; and action it ſelf is not quite free, being penned up and impriſoned within us. All under God hath a mixture of ill; carrieth in its honey a certaine ſting, that none draw neer, but they meet with diſpleaſure. A forcible argument that the end of creatures abide out of themſelves; where all per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fections abounding, ſweet conten
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151629:9"/>and reſt is to be found: and that is God.</p>
               <p n="3">3 In the ſupernaturall: by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon here is greater lack of ayd; more might and power required: the effects being greater, and of a farre nobler Kind. And if God was ſo charie and ſparing of his honour, as not to let paſſe the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of nature to himſelf; much more grace. Whence it is cleer, all flow from God, as ſtreames from the ſea; and are indowed with an innate or ingrafted Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion, to return back to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Now the happineſs of every thing conſiſting in content, and reſt, and content and reſt, in the injoying of its end; it followeth in man that there is a capacity of double happineſs, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural &amp; ſupernatural: he being ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of injoying God as he is the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151629:9"/>Author and end of nature, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſiſts naturall happineſſe; and as he is the Author and end of grace, wherein conſiſts ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall happineſſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4 But as nothing would have remained without Being, Except God had ſtretched forth his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent hand to beſtow it; ſo poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of Being, its bent and inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt take effect by his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous leave &amp; appointment: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, he is to preſcribe the means to an end, that is the Author and cauſe of the deſire thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whoſoever deſires to arrive ſafely at the bleſſed port of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, muſt baniſh far all ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit; and ſteer by no other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe, than that God hath touchd'; ſo may they ſaile right; els their courſe will be evermore crooked and deſperate; untill they doe run
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151629:10"/>themſelves upon the Rocks and Shelves of utter perdition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the will of God.</head>
               <p>PHiloſophers aſſure it for a very truth that the firſt of every kind, is the rule of the reſt in the ſame kind, and they are ſtrongly back'd by reaſon; for the nearer a thing draws in likeneſſe to its firſt, the more perfect it is, and ſo held to be. Whence may be eaſily gathered that the known Will of God is the rule Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount of all kinds, as well natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and humane as ſupernaturall, becauſe it was (as hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) before them all as Author &amp; cauſer thereof. I ſaid known, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard knowledg is ſo neceſſary &amp; requiſite to the compleating of a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151629:10"/>Rule, that wanting, it hath not right to challenge compliance. Now this knowledg coming from Propenſion, inſtinct, reaſon, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, or revelation, Propertie of ſpeech will yeild proof ſufficient that Propenſion and inſtinct are the light of naturall things, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of humane, tradition of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and revelation of ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, foraſmuch as none, meaning to be underſtood will deliver themſelves, that the Elements hold their ſeverall places by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, that Beaſts proſecute their ends by diſcourſe, that men attaine to what is paſt, and to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved without tradition and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation: Undoubtedly had not Chriſt revealed a conſiſtencie of Trinitie with Vnitie, a poſſibility of Hypoſtaticall Vnion, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition brought this revelation
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151629:11"/>down to us, theſe Myſteries would have been as <hi>terra incognita,</hi> not ſo much as ever dreamed of, <hi>Quis cognovit ſenſum Domini? Rom.</hi> 11. ſo as to ſpeak intelligibly and with truth, the will of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes known in things void of ſenſe by propenſion, inſenſible by inſtinct, inhumane, as to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent action, by reaſon, as to action paſt by tradition, in beliefe by revelation. Alwayes provided, concerning reaſon, that it be cleer of paſſion, and ſtrong, for in caſe of byas &amp; weakneſs, every one is to ſubmit to the wiſe and perfect, it being but meet that they that ſee ſhould have the Guidance of thoſe who are in darkenſſe, leaſt the blind leading the blinde both fall into diſorder. It onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines there being an ordinary and an extraordinarie Will, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151629:11"/>how they are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. In ſhort thus, if they agree, obedience ought to bee yeilded to both, if not, the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary muſt take place; Chriſt commanding the ſame with his father was equally to be obeyed, the Iſraelites according to the extraordinary will immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto them, might lawfully deſtroy the Cananites, all others were bound to obſerve the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary will of love and peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God onely having the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute ſoveraignty can command at pleaſure lives and fortunes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151629:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the way to happineſſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SIth God hath manifeſted his power by creating Man, and his goodneſſe by wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him a double happineſſe; doubtleſſe he hath not been back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to ſhew likewiſe his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in contriving the meanes to bring it to paſſe, and his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in making the meanes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable: otherwiſe he had wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led an impoſſibility and in vaine: for an end is not poſſible without a meanes; and a meanes is to no purpoſe, unleſſe it may be known. Now the meanes to an end requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting proportion and fitneſſe to the end it is ordained to; as the end of man is twofold, naturall and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151629:12"/>the meanes whereby he is to attaine to theſe ends muſt be ſo to.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sutable unto which, God hath appointed the meanes to mans naturall happineſſe to be acts of his underſtanding &amp; will, for by them he may ſeeke and finde out God, as he is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and end of nature; by theſe cleave and unite, and ſo injoy him. To mans ſupernaturall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, to be a conformity of faith to the Church; a conformity of hope to our Lords Prayer; and a conformity of Charity to the Commandements. A conformity of faith: without faith it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. He that believeth ſhall be ſaved; He that believeth not ſhall be condemned, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. To the Church. Going, teach ye all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151629:13"/>he that heareth you heareth me, <hi>Math.</hi> 16. He that hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the Church, let him be as a Heathen and a Publican. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity of hope. Hope in our. Lord, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 43. Bleſſed is the man who hopes in him, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. To our Lords Prayer. When you pray let it be our Father &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. Thus ſhall you pray, Our Father, &amp;c. <hi>Luke.</hi> 11. A conformity of Charity. If I give all to the poor, and have not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, it profiteth nothing, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. To the Commandments. This is the charity of God, that we, keepe his Commandements, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. If ye love me, keepe my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15,</p>
               <p n="3">3. By the firſt conformity Man comes to the knowledge of God, as he is the Author and end of Grace; by the ſecond relies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151629:13"/>his mercy and goodneſſe, that in due time he will grant and give thoſe good things, which Chriſt hath taught us to ask in his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: in the laſt he is taken with the beauty of his divine perfections, and ſo in joyes him in a higher, and more eminent manner. Both Happineſſes in this life are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, by reaſon of the glimmering light Man onely hath of God, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſame, they will be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated and perfected in the next; When Man, after a willing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with Gods grace in this, ſhall ſee him, not as in a looking glaſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. but face to face, as he is in himſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151629:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of the diverſities of faiths, hopes, and charities:</head>
               <p n="1">1 IT is demonſtrable, that there are divers ſortes of Faiths, Hopes, and Charities; as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall and Actuall Divine, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall and Actuall Humane: for ſome believe, hope for, and love ſupernaturall things, with the ſame, if not more eagerneſſe and fervency, than naturall; which Actions ſuppoſe, (as effects their proper and proportioned cauſes) ſupernatutall qualities: naturall not being able, (in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their meaner extract on and dignity) to give ſuch noble births. Thoſe are called divine, becauſe infuſed by Gods extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary power: theſe humane; for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151629:14"/>that they are acquired by the ſtrength of nature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Habituall divine are the ſupernaturall qualities them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; The Actuall divine are acts of the will of underſtanding, as raiſed and enabled to a higher pitch by thoſe ſupernaturall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: The Habituall humane are the acquired qualities themſelves, the Actuall humane are acts of the will and underſtanding, as inclined and fitted for act on by thoſe acquired qualities. The Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall and Actuall divine differ further from the Habituall and Actuall humane in their materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and formall objects; as alſo in the Means, whereby thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall objects come to knowledge; the materiall of Habituall and actuall divine being revealed Truths; the formal, Revelation: the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151629:15"/>materiall of habituall and actuall humane, unrevealed Truths; the formall the light of Reaſon, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reading or information. The meanes of habituall and actuall Divine, the Tradition of the Church, of Habituall and actuall humane the light of Reaſon, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reading or information.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Now foraſmuch as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity is a ſupernaturall building, contrived and framed by the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, to laſt for ever, of which Faith is the foundation; Hope the walls, and Charity the Roofe and perfection: The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formities expreſſed in the prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Chapter are to be underſtood of divine Faith, Hope &amp; Charity, and not of humane; becauſe all nature joyn'd &amp; gather'd in one, is not able to make a Being above Nature. And theſe are the vertues
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151629:15"/>call'd Theological, as having God immediatly for object; the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Siſters, three in number, but one in affection: none deſiring that which diſpleaſeth other. Greatneſs is their eſſentiall attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, yet Charity excells. St. <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. compares them together, extolls them all, but in the cloſe gives unto Charity the prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minence. And not undeſervedly, for ſhe is the enlivening ſoule of Faith, and Hope, and all the moral vertues: both they and theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (out of her company) as dead bodies, without life or motion, as to heaven and Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151629:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of the Churches power and infallibilitie in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SUppoſing it for granted' that Chriſts knowledge of Gods reaveled truth, and his power to convey the ſame to beliefe, raiſed his preaching &amp; teaching to the full height and perfection of a Rule of beliefe to the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; it cannot in reaſon be denied, he having communicated his ſaid knowledg and power to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, &amp; in them to the ſucceeding Churches, (as appears by his own words. All I have learnt of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have made known unto you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. As my father ſent
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151629:16"/>me, ſo I ſend you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.) but ſhe may challeng a like intereſt and right in reſpect of after-Chriſtians: whence it followeth, that all matters of Beliefe (as well other points as ſcripture) are to be taken upon her accompt and ciedit, and that whatſoever comes upon any other ſcore, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Apocryphall, and no way appertaining to the Obligation of Beleife.</p>
               <p n="2">2. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul declares this truth unto the Epheſians, aſſuring them, that they are builded upon no other foundation than the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. and <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 6. bidding them hold the traditions, and keep the <hi>depoſitum:</hi> and, again, if an Angell from heaven ſhall Evangelize any other, than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151629:17"/>what I have Evangelized to you, let him be accurſed. <hi>Gal.</hi> 7. The reaſon is cleare; becauſe the Rule of Beliefe, is the Meaſure of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, beyond which there is not any conformity, or obedience due from Beliefe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The uſuall colour for belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more or leſſe than the Church alloweth of, grounded upon her pretended ſubjection to Errour, is vain; inaſmuch, as that very Chriſt that ſtored her with knowledge of Gods revealed truth, and with power to convey the ſame, hath alſo indowed her with inerra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, whereby to convey it ſafely, and without danger of miſcarrying, by arming her proof aginſt all the enemies of truth: againſt ignorance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. To you it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151629:17"/>againſt darkneſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. you are the light of the world: againſt Errour and falſhood; <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. I will ſend unto you the ſpirit of truth, to remaine with you for ever. <hi>Jſaah</hi> 62. thou ſhalt no more be called forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: againſt Weakneſſe, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. ſhe is the Pillar and ground of truth. <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. Hell gates ſhall not prevaile againſt her. To make which good, and the worke ſure, Chriſt called his eternall father to his aid, prayed him, and was heard for his reverence, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. And to prevent and cut off all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of imagining; that theſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours beſtowed on the Church were not to ſurvive the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for a continuance in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Church, Chriſt adds, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I am with you all dayes to the end of the world <hi>Mat.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151629:18"/>28. ſoe as it muſt be ſaid; that either Chriſt was not of power to keep his Church from ſtraying, or that he wanted fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to make good his word.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The certanity divine faith requires to build on, is a further Evidence of the Churches infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, for how is it poſſible, Faith can be certain, if the Church that is to aſcertain it, be uncertain and fallible? look on the Churches compoſure and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and her ſtrength will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear yet more, by reaſon ſhe is framed and made up of men, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and ſpread over the world, who by this meanes, being of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Nations, different tempers and intereſts, neither could, nor can meet or conſpire to Cheat themſelves and poſterity with a lie. That men of themſelves are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151629:18"/>apt to miſtake and deceive is from the purpoſe. So the evangeliſts might have fallen ſhort of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming their taske. But as God holding their hands, and guiding their pennes, his holy word was truly and infallibly coucht on the ſacred leaves of the Bible; ſo aſſiſting and ſtrengthening his Church, ſhe becomes in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning faith powerfull and infallible.</p>
               <p>God is not tyed to this or tother; he is free to worke his wonders; where when and to whom he pleaſeth. Neither is there any diſproportion betwixt men thus aſſiſted and infallibility; it being not neceſſary for the production of a ſupernaturall effect, that every part of the total cauſe be ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural; for it is viſible to the eye that God frequently makes uſe of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condary
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151629:19"/>cauſes, in the production of ſupernaturall effects: in that of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. of hearing and preaching; in that of Grace, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18, 19, of Elements and words, in that of the blind man. <hi>Jo.</hi> 6. of ſpittle and earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Of the poſſibilitie of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</head>
               <p n="1">1 NOt onely that it is poſſible to keep the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but alſo that divers have kept them, is a truth ſo cleerly delivered, both in the old and new Teſtament, that there is cauſe to wonder, any can make queſtion thereof. In the old, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151629:19"/>of the Commandments ſayes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. They are not above but very near us in our Mouths, in our hearts to doe them. <hi>Noe Ezekias, Joſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Joſaphat, Aſa,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. <hi>6. 4</hi> Kings <hi>18. 2</hi> Paral. <hi>30. 4</hi> Kings <hi>22. 1</hi> Paral. <hi>15 2</hi> Paral. <hi>20.</hi> Tob. <hi>2.</hi> Iob <hi>1.17. 2</hi> Kings <hi>7. 3</hi> Kings <hi>9.</hi> Luke. <hi>2.</hi> Mat. <hi>11.21.</hi> Luke. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Joacham, Tobias, Job,</hi> kept them. In the New, Chriſt is no leſſe plain, My yoke is ſweet, my burden light. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>Zacharias, Elizabeth, the B.</hi> Virgin kept them. Gods conditional promiſes to Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid and his Poſterity could be termed no better than Jeers, unleſſe the commandements were poſſible. To what purpoſe ſo much perſwaſion in Books and Pulpits to live well, if the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151629:20"/>be impoſſible? is living well any other than keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Commandements? It is aſſuredly as rid culous as impious to tearm him a good liver that ſteales, murthers, and commits adultery, &amp;c. The juſtneſs of lawes, that inflict ſevere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon the breakers of the Commandements, are not at all conſiſtent with the impoſſibility of keeping them. Neceſſity is a good and forcible excuſe againſt the ſtrongeſt charge. The very light of Reaſon giveth teſtimonie to the Commandements poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they being all grounded upon Reaſon, and ſuited to her bent and inclination: The wickedeſt man alive cannot ſay with truth that he breaketh any Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without ſome ſecret check of conſcience.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151629:20"/>
               <p n="2">2. To alledge, that God onely requires mans indeavour, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to Chriſts expreſs words, which are not, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. If thou wilt come to heaven, endeavour to keep, but keep the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Many a good endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, as many a good purpoſe, burns in Hell. Heaven being the reward of doing, not of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring. Beſides it is equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall to endeavour impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lityes, and to deſire things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. Who could Chooſe but ſmile, to ſee one leap and skip, as ayming to ſoar &amp; fly in the Ayr, knowing it to be poſſible onely for Birds that are fitted with wings and feathers for the purpoſe? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to point at any particular, that doth keep the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is hard; no man knowing. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9. whether he be worthy
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151629:21"/>of love or hatred: But that all in generall may keep them, Chriſt himſelfe aſſures it, 2. <hi>Tim</hi> 2. Willing all to be ſaved. God wills nothing impoſſible, and he that wills the end wills the meanes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. True it is, neither Men nor Angells can love God as he is loveable, that's a perfection God onely is capable of; nevertheleſs it is in the power both of Angells and Men, to love God ſo far forth as the capacity of their condition reacheth, which, though it be a perfection of a lower degree, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it is ſufficient to denominate, and render the ſubject it is in perfect And even this I confeſs, is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> effect which Gods grace hath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chief hand in; but that is no Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for Man having his ſhare to Grace and Nature are not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151629:21"/>yea, Grace ſupporteth, nay, bettereth Nature: they may then joyn and endeavour together, as two of unequall ſtrength drawing a boat, one draweth more, but yet both draw. The part Grace acts in the working of ſalvation is to enlighten the underſtanding, move and enable the Will: The part Man acts is to comply with Grace, <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. to yield and conſent to her good Motions, <hi>Apocj.</hi> 3.20. Wherefore ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the work not of Grace alone, nor of man alone, but of Grace and Man joyning hand and heart together. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Auſtin</hi> (<hi>Tom.</hi> 10. <hi>Serm.</hi> 15. <hi>de verb. Apoſt. poſt. med.</hi>) ſpeakes truth, He that made you without you, will not juſtifie you without you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151629:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Of Religion.</head>
               <p n="1">1 SUch is the dread of Gods awfull Majeſty imprinted in Man, that the moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arous people, deem it a duty to ſet apart ſome time to worſhip him in; the light of reaſon teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that a certain return of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and veneration is due from the effect to its cauſe, whereby to expreſs ſubjection, gratitude and thankfullneſs: and albeit impiety wants not Proſelites, that reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Deity refuſe to do him homage; their folly is to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to lack of grace, and not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſaid light, as appeares by readineſs (obſerveable in them) to ſuffer for their opinion. If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> other world yield no Puniſher, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151629:22"/>Rewarder, no Hell, nor Heaven, it is madneſs to fear, and vain prodigality to give away life, the chief good, and beſt flower of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures garden.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This naturall propenſion to praiſe and magnify God begets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious acts, and Religious acts, that great moral vertue called Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: but Religion in a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon acception conſiſts in Beliefe, not humane, grounded upon Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but divine, relying on the Churches Authoritie, and the aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt. It is the doctrine of Chriſt delivered by himſelf in plain and expreſs terms. <hi>Mar.</hi> 16. All power is given to me in heaven and in earth, goe ye therefore and preach the Goſpell unto all nations; hee that believeth ſhall be ſaved,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151629:23"/>he that believeth not ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. <hi>Jo.</hi> 14. I will ſend unto you the holy Ghoſt, who ſhall teach you all Truth. Chriſt here ſpeakes to the Apoſtles the Church; giveth power to preach the Goſpell to the Apoſtles the Church, promiſeth ſalvation to Believers of the Apoſtles the Church, threatens damnation to unbelievers of the Apoſtles the Church: laſtly (that there may be no pretence for diſobedience) he aſſureth to the Apoſtles the Church a peculiar aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, whoſe proper effect is to keep power from exceſs and failing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Not a word of or to Reaſon; what colour then for attributing ſo much to Reaſon, and ſo little to the Church, as to deny Chriſt to have intruſted her with his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151629:23"/>Truth? as if the Goſpell were not Chriſts truth, or Chriſts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering the Church to preach the Goſpell, meant any other thing, than to intruſt her with his truth. Had Reaſon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence of Belief, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul would not have ſubjected Reaſon unto Belief, bidding all captivate the underſtanding to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Faith, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Indeed to give Reaſon the guidance of Belief, were to make the blind lead the blind, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15, For aſmuch as Reaſon is at a loſſe in the object of Belief, and in Belief it ſelf: the hotteſt zealots of Reaſon, having come ſhort of the one and the other, witneſs the Manichees, and other Heretiques. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe both are above Reaſon, as being high myſteries, and revealed ſo long ſince. But
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151629:24"/>Chriſtianity is not againſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and he is to be reputed ſilly and light, that haſteneth upon a truth, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 19. however propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, without examination of its credibility and conſiſtence with Nature, which muſt be the work of Reaſon; very true, nay more, Belief is beholding to Reaſon, even for diſcerning and finding out her guide, the true Church. But this onely amounts to an evidence, that Reaſon helps and contributes to belief, ſo doth preaching, reading; hearing, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="4">4 To be the guide of Belief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires further ability and skill, to lay open immediately to Belief Gods revealed Truth, a Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive belongs to the Church, and no other; as to whom alone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation was made. Whence
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151629:24"/>it followeth, that the Religion of Sectaryes is deficient &amp; vain, their belief being grounded upon ſome humane reſpect, and not upon the authority of the Church: and aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt. And conſequently that for them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the name of true Chrſtians, and to be ſtyled of the right Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, their onely way is to level at a perfection, that takes its riſe from an abſolute reſignation of their wills to the will of God, in order to the Church; which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſt is to become ſpiritually little ones, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. in reſemblance to naturall Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who are at beſt, when they moſt follow and obey their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents directions and commands. <hi>Hilar.</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151629:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8</hi> Of the Unity of Religion.</head>
               <p n="1">1 IT is an undoubted Maxime amongſt all that have any inſight in nature, that Being and Unity are inſeparably to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; inſomuch, that where Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, there Unity cannot be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. If then there be any ſuch thing as Religion, appointed by God for the ſalvation of ſoules, without all peradventure, it is one: Chriſt himſelf cleares the difficulty, ſaying, One ſheepfold and one Paſtor, <hi>Jo.</hi> 10. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul.</hi> declares no leſſe to the <hi>Epheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> willing them to affect unity, to the end that they may bee as one Body, one Spirit, one Faith, one Baptiſme, as God is one,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151629:25"/>
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4. And again, He gave ſome &amp;c. Untill we all meet in the unity of Belief?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now experience ſhews, that this unity of Religion, is an effect of acknowledging the Church for the Rule of Belief, it being viſible to the eye, that all that ſquare their Belief to the Church, are one in Religion; whereas they that take to themſelves other rules diſſent and jarre; of which no other reaſon can be given, but that the Church is all wayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and certain in her procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and clear in her expreſſions; other Rules, ſubject to uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, change, and obſcurity. The fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of the ſeverall Centers of fire and water inclines that to a conſtant aſcenſion, and this to a like deſcenſion. That Pilot were guilty of much ingratitude and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151629:26"/>to the Polars, that ſhould not yeild the guidance of the Ocean to the regularneſs of their motion. Contrariwiſe it is a plain demonſtration, that the inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of dayes and nights relates wholly to the wavering progreſs of the Sun: for every cauſe give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it hath, and no more; as certain effects of one and the ſame kind hold dependance of conſtant and certain cauſes, ſo uncertain effects of many and divers kindes, muſt needs belong to unconſtant and various cauſes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. True it is, that Scripture in it ſelf, that is, as it is the word of God, dictated by the holy Ghoſt, is certain and infallible; but to us, to wit, as it is lyable to this and t'other private interpretation, it is as uncertain and fallible, as man. Witneſs the many contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151629:26"/>interpretations we ſe dayly made of Scripture, which cannot poſſibly be all true: wherefore the concluſion iſſueth abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the Church is the onely fit Principle to unite Chriſtians together, and conſequently, that thoſe may deſpair of ever wearing the Badg and Ornament of true Chrſtianity, <hi>viz.</hi> unity, who dare with <hi>Core</hi> and the reſt of that rebellious Crew, bid defyance to the Church: <hi>Num.</hi> 16. <hi>Jude.</hi> 11.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151629:27"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> Of the goodneſſe of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cotholique Religion.</head>
               <p n="1">1 IF Excellency of nature and ſweetneſs of diſpoſition be ground enough to term a thing good, the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Religion may not unjuſtly claym that appellation. For firſt in her nature ſhe is made up of Excellencies, acknowledging a God Eternall, Almighty, Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, Wiſe, Good, Juſt, Maker &amp; Govern our of heaven &amp; Earth, One in nature, three in perſons, Father, Sonne and Holy Ghoſt, the Sonne to have taken hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fleſh, whereby to converſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151629:27"/>with man, to inſtruct and free him from the Bondage of Hell and ſinne, to have inſtituted ſeven Sacraments to ſupply the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of his ſpirituall life: Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme that he might be regenerate, Confirmation that he might grow ſtrong and able to profeſs his Faith before his enemies; the Euchariſt that he might be fed with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine grace, Penance that his Maladies and ſores of ſinne might be cured and healed, Extream unction, that he might be comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his laſt Agony againſt the uſuall aſſaults of the Divell, Holy Order, that he might be provided of ſpirituall teachers and Guides, Matrimony that he might be multiplyed in a holy and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall way: that he hath an endleſs ſtore of bliſs and happineſs to reward the good, and a like of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151629:28"/>pain and miſery to puniſh the bad, that he hath choſen and eſtabliſht ſome to propoſe and apply all thoſe good things to others: Now for her diſpoſition it is alſo good, teaching to love God above all, our Neighbours as our ſelves, to make an hearty and ready ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of both; of the former, by laying down wealth, honour, liberty, yea, life it ſelf rather than offend him, by building Churches and Oratories to praiſe and ſerve him in, by adorning and enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them for the better ſtirring up of devotion and reverence, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining and holding dear things appertaning to him or his, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a part dayes to remember his favours and benefits, by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping him for his own ſake with ſupream, his ſervants and beloved for his ſake with inferiour
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:151629:28"/>honour, by abhorring all manner of Idolatry: of the latter by bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in juries, leaving revenge to God, by forbearing even the leaſt wrong, and if any be done, by making full reparation and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends, by perſwading not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Religion, by relieving the poor &amp; needie with foundations of Hoſpitalls, Almſhouſes, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges &amp;c. by keeping faith with all, eſpecially Magiſtrates be they Catholiques, or Sectaries, Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or Infidells, good or bad, and that for very Conſcience ſake. Theſe are the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques tenets, and howbeit they admit of more, yet none being (what ever ignorance or malice hath noiſed to the contrary) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with theſe, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently agreeable to all ſorts of Governments; that State or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151629:29"/>that refuſes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defend them from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and oppreſſion appeares clearely wanting to its intereſt in not complying with Prudence and Iuffice, which bid to love and cheriſh all ſafe and faſt ſubjects. O but Catholiques have a depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the Pope, who is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Prince, they haue ſo, but not as he is a temporall Prince, for ſo he is confined within certain territories of Italy and France, their relation to him is onely as hee is their common ſpirituall Father, whoſe office be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to keep off Rebellion, and to teach obedience, cannot endanger the leaſt. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter and the reſt of the Apoſtles were forreigners to ſeverall Provinces, the intereſt of Chriſt brought them to, yet in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard their power was ſpirituall,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151629:29"/>the Civill Magiſtrate had no cauſe to fear, but rather to rejoyce, as at a Good drawing towards them. God having given the ſpirituall power as the ſoul to the body for comfort and ſupport, not for hurt or anoyance: what ſay you then to the practiſe of ſeverall Popes: I ſay that Popes may prevaricate and exceed their Commiſſion, and in caſe they doe that, they are to ſtand by themſelves: I, &amp; ſtrange caſes are maintained, by ſome which ſeem to induce to murder, theft, lying, caſes appertain not to religion but to action, whoſe rule is reaſon, and not revelation, for God hath not revealed all belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to charitie, as he hath in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Faith Now reaſon being in moſt men weak and by aſt by paſſion or intereſt, what cauſe is there ſo much to wonder at the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151629:30"/>ſtrangeneſs of concluſions reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereof; the worſt can be inferred hence is that ſectaries ſeem void of reaſon, that make reaſon the rule of their belief, which is ſo defective and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in the reach, even of naturall, and morall truths. Then the ſtewes are allowed in ſeverall places. A clear miſtake, they are onely permitted, that is not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred or puniſht, for no Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke approves of Whoredome, as an act well done, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſignification of allowing: now not to hinder or not to puniſh ſome kind of ſinne, at leaſt wiſe in certain cauſes is not ill, or if it be, how can God bee good, who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitts all manner of ſinne? Nay, the forbearance to is but from vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, there being all the ſweet and charitable meanes uſed to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151629:30"/>take off of that lew'd way, as pious exhortations, godly ſermons, offers of entertainment in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious houſes founded of purpoſe for ſuch as repent, laſtly an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of an unchriſtian like buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to thoſe that Dye impenitent. Further the Inquiſition admits of no perſwaſion but her own. The Inquiſition hath leſſe relation to religion, than caſes, being a meer peice of State Policy, as is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in France and Germany, where Catholicke Religion bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſway, the Inquiſition is not at all owned, Proteſtants en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying in both places as much freedome of Conſcience as Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes themſelves; At leaſt wiſe it is not to be denied, that the Romiſh Religion allowes of Breaking of faith with ſectaries, upon which accompt outrages
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151629:31"/>have been committed. Moſt falſe! ſhe abhominates all ſuch doctrine as deſtructive to fidelity, which ſhe magnifies as the ground of Iuſtice, Whence then this Monſter? Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from ill compoſure, weak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, depraved will: croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked nature prompts to ill, weak underſtanding conceives amiſſe, depraved will receiving erronious judgment for good and currant, muſters her forces, ſtirs up Anger and hatred, which heightned, trample under foot all regard of Religion &amp; vertue, and tranſports to diſorder and miſchief; ſo that ill compoſure, weak underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, depraved will, wild paſſions and not Religion were the guilty, let them ſuffer and not thoſe who in order to their Religion hate all barbarouſneſs in opinion, keep under and curb unruly &amp; naughty
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151629:31"/>paſſions. It were a ſtrang peice of Iuſtice to puniſh equally flyers and followers of Theft and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Scripture is expreſs for every one to abide the ſhame of his own ſinne: wherefore the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence ſeemes generall to free and keep inocency from moleſtation and trouble.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:151629:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10</hi> Of the truth of the Roman Catholique Religion.</head>
               <p n="1">1 I Strange at the Partiality &amp; inconſequence of thoſe who Juſtify the Enemies of the Roman Catholique Religion, whiles they are in a readineſs to condemne of folly &amp; perverſneſs; ſuch as ſhould goe about to call in queſtion the conqueſt of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour. I ſay I ſtrange at it, in as much as the evidence of the conqueſt comes farre ſhort of the evidence of the Roman Catholique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that amounting one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to an atteſtation from the oral tradition and hiſtory of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whereas this, beſides the oral tradition and hiſtory of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151629:32"/>hath the like teſtimony of <hi>France, Spain, Italy, Germany, Greece, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Affrica,</hi> all una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly witneſſing that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholick Religion was firſt taught and delivered by Chriſt, as may appear to any that will lay aſide prejudice, &amp; make a through enquiry of the truth. Whence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulteth, that if it be ridiculous and abſurd to queſtion the conqueſt, much more is it repugnant to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to doubt of the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Religion. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Conqueſt is preferred by ſome as more evident, in regard it was never queſtioned, the Roman Catholique Religion often. What then? queſtioning is no mark of falſhood, The Trinity, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, the Scriptures have been all queſtioned, and yet are confeſſedly true: queſtioning ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151629:33"/>rather ignorance and malice in the Queſtioner, than want of truth in the thing queſtioned: whereto adde that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholique Religion was ſometime unqueſtioned, yea ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged for true even by them that afterwards queſtioned its truth. Others will oppoſe that the Pope bearing great ſway in the world might and did firſt bring in the Roman Catholique Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; Chriſt bore greater, why not he? now that Chriſt and not the Pope did firſt teach &amp; deliver the Roman Catholique Religion, Tradition both oral, and hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call give teſtimonie, here is the proper proof of a thing done ſo many Ages paſt, their onely ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and ſaying; can there be any Compariſon in the deſert of credit? but to ſhew further even
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151629:33"/>an impoſſibility in theſe oppoſers aſſertion, I muſt obſerve unto them that the Rule of the Catholique Church is not the Popes pleaſure; as they fondly imagine, but (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> calls it) the <hi>depoſitum</hi> which importing to hold what was delivered, and to recieve no other for divine truth, could not but defeat this pretended Pope of all poſſibility of bringing in a Religion of his own coyning, for either he kept to the Rule of the Catholique Church, or he did not, if he kept to the Rule of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, what he taught was delivered to him, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not invented by him, if he did not, the generalitie of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans could not follow his example; becauſe the univerſality of contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cauſes is unchangeable, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt's iterated promiſes of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151629:34"/>the holy Ghoſts aſſiſtance would not ſuffer it. Now the Roman Catholique Religion having been generally received for a divine truth, maketh it altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any Pope to be or to have been the firſt Contriver of it. What is further alledged in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Religion from perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, power and cuſtome makes againſt other Religions which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon fancy (ſhewing that nimbleneſſe of wit &amp; volubility of tongue may gain belief of ſuch power grown terrible fright into a profeſſion of the ſame, and cuſtome give a good likeing and zeal of both; <hi>So Luther</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> perſwaded their Novelties, Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> forced a profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, and cuſtome rendred them to moſt ſeeming good, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151629:34"/>true) and not againſt the Roman Catholique Religion that hath its relyance upon the certain uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of Tradition, &amp; Chriſt's never failing aſſurance of the holy Ghoſts aſſiſtance, and which by reaſon of its auſterity and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of its profoundneſs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſibility, of its reſtleſs ayming at proficiency and growth in vertue and perfection, had to enter the liſts and encounter with them all, with fleſh and blood; as to which ſuffering and pain would be troubleſome, and diſpleaſing; with reaſon as to which heavenly myſteries would ſeem ſtrange and mazefull; with power as to which new endeavours would be ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and provoking: to Cuſtome; as to which Change would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant and deſtructive. To ſay truth, it is a clear demonſtration
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151629:35"/>of truth in the Roman Catholique Religion, that having to ſtruggle with fleſh and blood, with the bloody crueltyes of the fierceſt Tyrants, it ſhould be able maugre all their oppoſitions by meanes of a few contemplible men to prevail, ſo as to gain, and keep the Dominion and maſtery of the cheifeſt and largeſt part of the Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151629:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 11.</hi> Of ſet Prayer.</head>
               <p>EXtravagancies being ſimpton's and tokens of diſtemper, it is a plain caſe, that the traducers of ſet Prayer are not well at eaſe. For what more extravagant than to levell and ſtrike at the very Acts of Chriſt and his Church as theſe doe, ſcripture declaring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely, that as well the one as the other have made and impoſed ſet prayer; mark well the words. <hi>When ye pray Mat.</hi> 6. <hi>let it be Our father:</hi> loſet prayer made and impoſed by Chriſt. <hi>Have ye a form of ſound words.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>Obſerve them that walk, ſo as you have our form: ſing unto our Lord in Pſalms, hymns &amp; Canticles, Phil.</hi> 3
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151629:36"/>Here the Church in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul makes and impoſes ſet Prayer; and as for their power in doing it, Chriſt ſayes firſt for himſelf; <hi>All power is given unto me in heaven and in earth. John.</hi> 14. next for the Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. <hi>hee that heares you heares me,</hi> neither grant is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or reſtrained, and the end of both is to inſtruct in all Chrſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an duty, therefore muſt needs reach prayer as a chief part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: I quarrel not with extemporary prayer in gifted perſons, if all ought to improve their talents, why ſhould any be debarred the uſe which is the meanes to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement? All I contend is, that Chriſtians are to have a regard of decency and order, for that Chriſt (who is the God of order and not of confuſion) came not to beſtow the beautifull and pretious jewell
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151629:36"/>of Chriſtianity upon a confuſed and hell-like multitude, but upon a well ordered company, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a perfect ſubordination of inferiours to ſuperiours, amongſt whom as there is a commanding power, ſo there is a duty to obey a power, being to ſmall purpoſe; unleſs it can challenge obſervance. Nevertheleſs ſuperiors having not tyed up all inferiours actions, but left ſome looſe and free as extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary power &amp;c, inferiours may pray at pleaſure of their private ſtore, ſo as they doe not paſſe their bounds to find fault and claſh with ſuperiours; it is not at all miſbecoming a houſeholder to order his family after his own mode, if it be done without oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to, or contempt of the lawes; but ſhould the ſun it ſelf in its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall motion reſiſt or thwart the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151629:37"/>common motion of the heavens, it muſt undoubtedly diſcompoſe &amp; marre the melodiouſneſs of their harmony. The Exception againſt ſet prayer that it hinders attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and elevation, hath not the leaſt ground, becauſe extempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayer requiring ſtudy is rather apt to diſtract and beat down, whiles it ſeeks and dives to find out what to ſay, whereas ſet prayer, being made to our hands, needs no ſtudy, and conſequently brings no ſuch inconvenience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151629:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> Of the meanes to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation with God.</head>
               <p>HAving thus endeavoured to ſet forth a ſound and good Chriſtian, handſomeneſs of order requires to declare next a Remedy for ſuch as are diſeaſed and ill, in complyance wherewith I ſhall ſay, that Chriſt hath appointed repentance, as the onely ſafe and ſure meanes to reconciliation, and doubtleſs ſo it is, for diſeaſes as well ſpirituall as corporall are properly to be cured by contraries, and the Spirituall diſeaſe of an ill Chriſtian in pride &amp; malice, whoſe contraries are faith, humility, fear, Love, ſorrow hope, purpoſe of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, confeſſion and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, all which are the eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151629:38"/>of Repentance; and being ſoe, argue deſperateneſs in thoſe that dare hazard their reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation upon confidence of forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which rather ſydes with than oppoſes their diſeaſe, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by ſtating the caſe betwixt man and man thus; a Maſter bearing affection to his ſervant beſtowes on him favours and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, this ſervant inſtead of deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving growes ſavage and inſolent, inſomuch that he reviles and abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes his good Maſter, afterwards reflecting upon his ingratitude, calls to mind, his Maſters worth, &amp; thence raiſeth to himſelf a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that he hath forgiven him. Clearly this proceeding is ſo far from leſſening, that it increaſeth this ſervants offence, as adding thereto preſumption. Now Gods friendſhip ſurpaſſing mans imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151629:38"/>the breach of it muſt be worſe, and conſequently a greater and more exact reparation is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. It behooveth then every Chriſtan deſirous of ſpirituall health to beware of this imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent and pernitious confidence, and when Conſcience accuſes of ſinne, to take Chriſts Remedie as followeth: in the firſt place by way of Preparative, crave Gods aſſiſtance, then ſtir up an Act of humility by acknowledging your unworthineſs, an act of faith by conſidering Gods omnipotence &amp; veracitie, an Act of fear by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his ſeverity in punniſhing ſinne, an Act of love by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his goodneſs in creating, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, redeeming and adopting you to be his Child, an Act of ſorrow by conſidering his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and your loſſe, an Act of hope
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151629:39"/>by conſidering his promiſes of mercy, which done make a firm purpoſe to doe ſo no more, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs your fault; and take upon you ſome Penance of Prayer, faſting or Almes-deeds in part of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the injury offered. This way may benefit Chriſtians of all perſwaſions, but can hurt none, becauſe Religion, though it be above, yet it is not againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and prudence allowes you, encourageth the tryall of ſafe and harmleſs meanes: great affaires ſeldom complain of too much care and diligence, there being in good no danger of exceſs. And here it will not be unſeaſonable to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the unjuſtneſs of ſectaries, who impute eaſineſs to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, avouching that according to their Religion, a bare confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſinns to a Preiſt pacifies
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151629:39"/>and appeaſes God, whereas beſides confeſſion, (not to ſpeak of its horridneſs &amp; a verſeneſs to nature) they hold as neceſſary all the other above mentioned Acts, that if any one bee wanting, their confeſſions become invalid and ſacrilegious. Above all their ſtrangeneſs breakes out in their complaint of uneveneſs in their way, as though it were ſuch a matter to believe Chriſtes merits who is the ſource and fountain of all worth, or to have a confidence in God whoſe goodneſs traſcends all that can be ſinne, and yet this is the very quinteſſence of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſites to reconciliation with God, albeit their ſinnes ſhould ſwell to drown in loudneſs the cryes of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:151629:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> Of the Spirit of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THe ſpirit of God in God is as God, every where; I fill heaven and earth <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. So as in this ſenſe none can be abſent from his eſſence, preſence, nor ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. But the queſtion runs of the effects thereof, which depending upon his will, are confined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in narrower limits. This truth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears bright in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iohn, where he forbiddeth to give credit <hi>to every ſpirit, Jo.</hi> 1.4. To deny that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God is active &amp; fruitfull in ſome, were to fall into another extream, and in effect to call Gods goodneſs &amp; mercy in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151629:40"/>to know and diſcern who they be, the onely way is to ſee their warrant, and examine their works. If their warrant prove that of Miracles, and their workes good, doubtleſs they have the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Gods ſpirit; if otherwiſe, they are at the beſt but pretence makers, and uſhers of innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This way muſt needes be true and ſure, becauſe Chriſt and Saint Paul taught it, and it ſtands with right reaſon; for bare ſayings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proof are ſounds of want and emptineſs; and the capacity of every Agent being to produce effects like it ſelf, it is as impoſſible for the ſpirit of God (that is all goodneſs) to be the author of ill, as for a reaſonable creature to beget an unreaſonable, or heat to cauſe cold. Whence it is plain,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151629:41"/>that the ſpirit of Spiritiſts is a falſe impoſture, a meer figment and deluſion, in as much as it is deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Miracles, and induceth to ill; it perſwading a diſloyall defection from our Lords Prayer, the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Church;<note place="margin">Bucer in Mat. <hi>6.</hi> Calvin. in Mat. <hi>6.</hi> Luther. de Moyſe. Zuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glius in explan. art. <hi>16.</hi> Tindal in Fox his acts pa. <hi>140.</hi> edit An. <hi>1610.</hi>
                  </note> in the conſonancy and diſſonancy to which conſiſt the goodneſs and bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all Actions. All actions being good or bad, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they are conform or difforme to Gods known will, which is apparently manifeſted in the aforeſaid. Hereto adde, that the ſpirit of Spiritiſts promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth things contrary and imcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent each with other; <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> aſſert the reallity of Chriſts'
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151629:41"/>body, Zuinglians maintain a bare figure, Calviniſts differ from both, which cannot befall the ſpirit of God; for ſo the ſpirit of truth might become the ſpirit of Errour and falſhood.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To ſay that God is no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of perſons, that his ſpirit being free, may breath on whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, is out of the matter in hand; here being no diſpute of Gods power, what he may doe, but of his will, what he doth. Their other ground for inſpiration upon the aſſurance of Conſcience, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Paul.</hi> and <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtin</hi> convinced long ſince of weakneſs and coze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage. <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Paul,</hi> when for yielding to Conſcience in perſecuting the primitive Chriſtians, he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged himſelf unworthy of the name of an Apoſtle 1, <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtin,</hi> when he ſharpned
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151629:42"/>his pen againſt Manichiſme, which before in obedience to Conſcience he upheld and defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Conſcience can have no greater certainty than the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that gave it being; and the underſtanding, experience teacheth to be ſo bad an aymer, that in the ſearch of truth, it oftner miſſes than hits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:151629:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 14.</hi> Of the Spiritiſts Rule of faith.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THe Rule of faith may be conſidered in it ſelf, or in reſpect of us; in it ſelf it is Gods revealed truth; in reſpect of us, it is the ſame truth expreſſed to us. Thus far Catholiques and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts agree, their difference is about the expreſſion. Theſe holding, that it is that of their private ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit joyned to that of Scripture onely; Thoſe, that it is that of the Church, Scripture bearing wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of her truth. This latter is clear, by what hath been already ſaid in the third Chapter, and will appear yet more by diſproving
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151629:43"/>the former. Which for the firſt part, that it is falſe and ſpurious, <hi>Saint Peter</hi> gives evidence point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blank, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>No interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture by private ſpirit. Saint Paul</hi> ſpeakes to the ſame effect, where he wiſheth (2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.) to captivate the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the obedience of faith. And our Saviour confirms both teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, obliging all under pain of damnation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Church. If the Church be to ſway, every private ſpirit muſt ſtoop and obey; <hi>for none can ſerve two Maſters, Luke.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the ſecond, that it is defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Scripture atteſteth, referring to the Church, and reaſon makes it good. For as much as the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion Faith requires, ought to be as full and ample, as the duty of Faith; that is, it muſt be able to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151629:43"/>informe the underſtanding in all it ſtands bound to give aſſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; wherein the expreſſion of Scripture alone is defective; it not declaring ſundry pointes Chriſtians acknowledge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves bound to believe. To wit, that thoſe bookes of Scripture, which are received for Canonicall, are ſo indeed. That ſome are Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, other ſome Apocryphall. That they are determinately theſe or others. That the Jewes Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aoth is to be neglected and laid aſide, and the Sunday ſolemnized. That the Creed is authenticke, and truely the Apoſtles. That it is lawfull to eate ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gled meates and blood. But theſe men pleaſe themſelves with onely talke of Scripture; for were Scripture (as they pretend) the Rule of their beliefe, though it containes divers
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151629:44"/>truths; yet thoſe truths meeting and becoming one in Revelation, they would all perfectly agree, not onely <hi>Lutherans</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Calviniſts</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but likewiſe <hi>Lutherans</hi> with <hi>Zuinglians,</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> with both; it being the propertie of unity to unite and make one all that conforme to the ſame: Whereas happening quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it is a manifeſt ſigne, that fancy, under ſpecious pretences of Scripture &amp; the Spirit, is the great Idol they do homage to; <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> to <hi>Luthers, Zuinglians</hi> to <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and <hi>Calviniſts</hi> to <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:151629:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 15.</hi> Of the Proteſtant Church.</head>
               <p>Proteſtants caſt a fairer ſhine than the Spiritiſts, and certes were their Church as true as it is ſeeming, they could not be juſtly taxed. But all is not gold that gliſters, Satan is apt to transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. Falſhood it ſelf is not ſeldome ſeen in the habili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of truth; and therefore this Chapter pretends to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the many ſhapes Proteſtants put their Church in, to make her paſs for true.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:151629:45"/>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p>The firſt is, Proteſtants are a company of Chriſtans under the government of Biſhops &amp; Paſtors, that have power and authority from Chriſt and his Apoſtles to adminiſter the Sacraments, and preach the word of God: But ſuch a company is the true Church, therefore Proteſtants are the true Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>ANSWER</head>
                  <p n="1">1 Neither Chriſt nor the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ever conferred any power or Authority on Proteſtant Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops and Paſtors; they were dead and gone, long before theſe had any being. To give Power and Authority of this nature, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth preſence of the Giver: ſo was God preſent to <hi>Moſes, Exod:</hi> 3.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151629:45"/>
                     <hi>Chriſt to his diſciples, Mat.</hi> 6.28. Neither is their any Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Monument extant to ſhew that the power or Authority Chriſt bequeathed, ſhould lye ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and dead for ſuch a tract of time, and then be brought to light and revived when Proteſtant Biſhops and Paſtors ſprang up, or that it was for them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It will be ſaid, Chriſt and the Apoſtles ſhared their power to Proteſtant Biſhops mediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, immediately to thoſe lived in their dayes; and thoſe to others downe to theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> By this is implyed a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of ſucceſſion in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhops and Paſtors, ever ſince Chriſt &amp; the Apoſtles; it is not concievable any other way, how power could be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted from one hand to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:151629:46"/>as is averred; as alſo a viſibilite of the ſame; for as much as it was their partes to preach the word of God, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter the Sacraments; if viſible, they may be produced, they ought to be produced: they may, becauſe that power is vaine and fictitious, that is not reducible to act, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. They ought, becauſe Biſhops and Paſtors in caſe of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, are to give an accompt of their calling, <hi>Luke.</hi> 7. as well to ſettle the wavering, as to bend and make ſupple the ſtifneſs of ſtubborne misbelievers. 1 <hi>Peter.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. How neceſſary this is, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> admirably well vrged,<note place="margin">Lib de praeſcrip. Iren. adver. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. Hieron. in Lucifer. Optat. lib. <hi>2.</hi> contra Parmen.</note> when he bad the Sectaries of his time <hi>let him ſee the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their Biſhops &amp; Paſtors. Likewiſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151629:46"/>Optatus, the Origin of your Chaire, ſhews yee, that needs will challenge to your ſelves the holy Church: St. Auſtin</hi> came not behind theſe in preſſing the neceſſity of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and derivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Auguſtin de u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilit. credend. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. cont. Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum Manich.</note> where he inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth them to be of force to hold &amp; keep him in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of the Church. <hi>There keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me,</hi> ſaid that great Saint, <hi>in the Church, the ſucceſſion of Prieſts from the very ſitting of St. Peter, to whom our Lord after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection committed the feeding of his ſheepe, even to this preſent Biſhop.</hi> And well did it become the Pious zeale of thoſe ornaments &amp; lights of Gods Church, to ſhew earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; vehemency in this behalfe, inaſmuch as derivation of ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:151629:47"/>is ſo proper to the true Church, that it cannot agree to any falſe, as, <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Hierom (in Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam.</hi> 1.) obſerveth, aſſuring Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to have <hi>no ſuch riches as come to men, by plain inheritance from their fathers:</hi> and as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in it ſelfe; by reaſon the true Church was planted and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, before any falſe began: The Parable of the good man, ſowing firſt good ſeed, and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my over-ſowing Cockle, evince no leſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. Therefore muſt needs be a <hi>non plus ultra,</hi> a ſtopp &amp; bar, betwixt whatſoever Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Church and Chriſt, to keep off the like continuation of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It will be ſaid, if derivation of ſucceſſion be a ſure Marke of the true Church, Arians &amp; Turkes may claim the true Church,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151629:47"/>Arians deriving themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out interruption from <hi>Arius,</hi> and the Turks from <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl: Arian</hi> and <hi>Turk</hi> deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion climb not ſo high as Chriſt, it reacheth no further than <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Mahomet,</hi> who grew up long after Chriſt: the Argument from ſucceſſion is not grounded upon any ſucceſſion, but upon derivati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſucceſſion from the Apoſtles and Chriſt; and that holds good: becauſe Chriſt was not onely man, but God alſo: and therefore had power to conſtitute a true Church; <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Mahomet</hi> were no more than men, who may not aſſume any ſuch prerogative. So that derivation of ſucceſſion from them onely demonſtrates them to have been the Founders and beginners of <hi>Arianiſme</hi> and <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:151629:48"/>
                  <p n="5">5. It will be ſaid, divers Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were contemporary with Chriſt; therefore that argues Antiquity onely not Truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repl.</hi> It may be ſeverall Sectaries had the honour to ſee ſome part of the time Chriſt lived in, but not his inſtitution, that was a ſpeciall favour reſerved for, &amp; onely gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his deare ſpouſe the Church. Sectaryes crept in after, as oppoſers of Chriſts inſtitution.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It will be ſaid, There have been named in ſeverall ages the <hi>Albigenſes,</hi> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolici,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Oſiand. Epitom. AEn. Sylvius de geſt. Bohem. Guid Carmel in Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſ. Antoninus Luxemberg. in paup. de Lugdun. Vſpergens chron. <hi>212.</hi> Ceſar. Ciſtert. dial. <hi>5.</hi> Vincent. ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum hiſt Prateolus. Sandeus.</note> 
                     <hi>Wickliffe, Hus. Repl.</hi> None of theſe were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, they hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:151629:48"/>not in all points with them, nor yet with themſelves, asis to be ſeen in <hi>Oſiander, Aeneas Sylvius,</hi> and other approved Hiſtorians. Beſides there was a great diſtance between them and the Apoſtles, in which they could not be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; for as much as they were not begun, or were quite extinct.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>2</head>
                  <p>Another ſhape is, Luther deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Catholiques, Catholiques from the Apoſtles; therefore Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants had their originall from the Apoſtles; they deriving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves uninterruptedly from <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151629:49"/>
                  <head>ANSWER</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Proteſtants derivation from <hi>Luther</hi> is frivolous, and of no weight; <hi>Luther</hi> wanting Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Authority, without which all Ordinations are null and fruſtrate; by the confeſſions of the cheif Proteſtants themſelves: See <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia, Sutcliffe, Bilſon, Andrews, White, Maſon, Mountague, Hall</hi> and others.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It will be ſaid, <hi>Luther</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Epiſcopal power immediately from God. <hi>Repl.</hi> Such a power being extraordinary, is alwayes accompained with that of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, as appeared in <hi>Moyſes, Exod.</hi> 3. and the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Luther</hi> never wrought Miracle; neither did he ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any ſuch gift, the ſeaſon
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151629:49"/>of Miracles (as ſome of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples avouch) being than paſt. And for his wonders alleadged in drawing ſo many after him, mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre the Pope, Emperour, and other Potentates, it ſhews onely a ſtrange itching in men after Novelties, &amp; proneneſs to <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinage. Arius</hi> in a ſhorter ſpace lead away far more, and greater ones, (that to uſe Saint <hi>Hieroms</hi> words, <hi>cont. Lucifer.</hi>) <hi>the world did groan again, to ſee it ſelf on a ſuddain become Arian.</hi> But this could be no Miracle; for Miracles are done for the aſſerting of truths, &amp; it was moſt untrue, that Chriſt was not God, that he was not equall to his eternall father, as <hi>Arius</hi> contended.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It will be ſaid, it was Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous in the Apoſtles, to convert thouſands to the faith of Chriſt,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151629:50"/>in a time of greateſt oppoſition and reſiſtance. <hi>Repl.</hi> In them it was, it being a work of too high a nature for the undertaking of poor illiterate men, to perſwade a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſo contrary to fleſh and blood, as mortification of Wills, Faſting, Chaſtity, &amp;c. <hi>Luther</hi> was a man of learning and parts, who had onely to inſtil a doctrine acceptable and pleaſing to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pravedneſs of nature; to perform which needed not abilities other than naturall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>3</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> third ſhape is, Proteſtants re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived their Miſſion from Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Biſhops in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes and ſince.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:151629:50"/>
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. If ſome did, which is to be proved, Nay the contrary ſeemes demonſtrated by <hi>Doctor Champ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,</hi> it is evident the greater part did not; and what a Church muſt that company make, of which moſt are judged fit to preach the word of God, and adminiſter the Sacraments without authority? But admit the calling of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhops and Paſtours were right in all of them, it would not follow that the Proteſtant Church is true, ſo long as ſhe advanceth Proteſtaniſme, contrary to the meaning of the Catholique Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, who never impowr'd any, but in relation to the ſetting up, and upholding of Catholique Religion.</p>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151629:51"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Furthermore, Communion with the true Church being as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a requiſite to the making up of a true Church, as union of parts to the compleating of a naturall body; what colour for truth in the Proteſtant Church, that is at variance with the Catholique, of whom ſhe gloryeth to have her power, and which ſhe confeſſeth to be a true Church: whereto adde, that Proteſtants derivation from Catholiques, is not proof for a perſonall ſucceſſion of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Paſtours agreeing in all points with Proteſtants, which ought to be the ſcope and ayme of that derivation: it being not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of Proteſtants to deduce a ſucceſſion from Chriſt and his Apoſtles of <hi>men meerly ſent,</hi> but withall <hi>profeſſing the doctrine maintained in the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:151629:51"/>For although doctrine be no mark of the true Church (as ſhall be ſhewn hereafter) nevertheleſs it is her inſeparable Mate; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that where true Doctrine is wanting, there the true Church cannot be; Chriſt having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted her with his truth, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained her keeper and preſerver thereof.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It will be ſaid, ſuch a ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be ſhewn, but mingled pale-male with Catholiques, as corn with chaffe, good fiſh with bad, conformably to Scripture; comparing the Church to a barn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>floor, where there is corn and chaffe together, <hi>Math.</hi> 3. to a Net repleniſhed with all ſortes of fiſh, <hi>Math.</hi> 13. <hi>Repl.</hi> This mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt have been either of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and Catholique doctrine in the ſame company of men, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151629:52"/>profeſſion of both, or in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall companies; one profeſſing one, another the other: It could not be the former, becauſe that would be a clear argument that the Church hath erred; contrary to what was proved in the fift Chapter. Beſides the name of Proteſtant to this company would be very improper, holding a Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine inconſiſtent with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. Surely, whoſoever over and above the Proteſtant Doctine, ſhould profeſs the Arian, or Neſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, would deem himſelf jeered and laughed at, to hear himſelf ſtyled by the name of Proteſtant: Doctrine being in nature much like unto number, the leaſt addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or diminution altering its kind, and grounding a new deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. Nor the latter, in as much as there is <hi>no agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151629:52"/>the Temple of God and Idols, no concord with Chriſt and Belial.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. The Arke of God and Dagon may not ſtand together, 1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 5. It were a ſtrange exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if the Church, unparaleld for love to her ſpouſe, that profeſſeth ſo much to truth, and ſtrictly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth ill company (as dangerous to her Children) ſhould receive into her company <hi>Lyers</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novatours.</hi> This would leave a ſtain upon her reputation, make her ſincerity be ſuſpected, her Doctrine contemned and deſpiſed. But ſhe who is, <hi>all fair. Cant.</hi> 6. <hi>Without ſpot or wrinkle. Epeſ.</hi> 5. is free from any ſuch guilt; Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries being as hideous and hatefull in her ſight, as their ſuggeſtions are full of poyſon and deſtructive to ſoules.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. It will be ſaid, Proteſtant
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151629:53"/>Biſhops and Paſtours, were not ſo near mingled with Catholiques, as either to believe or profeſs their Doctrine; they onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed and covered their own, for fear of the formidable rigour of Catholiques. <hi>Repl.</hi> ſuch Biſhops and Paſtours could neither be true, nor make a ſaving Church. Not true, becauſe the Miſſion of true Biſhops and Paſtours being founded upon perſecution and ſuffering (<hi>Loe, I ſend you as ſheep among Wolves. Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Luke.</hi> 11.) it is proper for them to fear no colours: Cruelty in her gaſtli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hue is not able to fright or daunt them from preaching the word of God, and adminiſtring the Sacraments. The Apoſtles gave teſtimony to this truth, when commanded by higher powers to forbear mentioning
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151629:53"/>Chriſt or his actions, they bravely and with ſtoutneſs reported that they could not chooſe, but declare, <hi>What they had ſeen and heard;</hi> yea, even outraged and ill entreated for this behalf, they went away <hi>glad and rejoycing, to be thought worthy to ſuffer for the name of Jeſus. Acts.</hi> 5. All the glorious Martyrs and Confeſſours confirm the ſame, by their profeſſion of faith amidſt the loathſome ſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of cloſe Priſons; and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble torments of bloody perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Nor make up a ſaving Church; by reaſon profeſſion of Faith is neceſſary to ſalvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>In heart it is believed to juſtice, by mouth profeſſion is made unto Salvation. Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>He that denies me to men: I will denie him before my father &amp;c.</hi> The
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151629:54"/>Compariſons are meant of private men for matter of manners, &amp; not of any mixture of true and falſe Doctrine, Orthodoxall &amp; Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Biſhops &amp; Paſtours together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <p>A fourth ſhape is, in all ages ſince Chriſt and his Apoſtles there have been Proteſtant Biſhops and Paſtours, but through the negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of men, and hard fate of times, their names have miſcarried and periſh'd. And as it is no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, many famous Romans and Graecians are not named, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore never were any ſuch men; ſo it is no leſs falſ a ſequell, Proteſtant Biſhops and Paſtours are not mentioned all the way from Chriſt and the Apoſtles, therefore they were ſometimes wanting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:151629:54"/>
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. It is not the ſame of private men, and of Biſhops and Paſtours: Theſe have Chriſts Warrant and aſſurance for a Continuance of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility, ſo have not thoſe, <hi>Math.</hi> 28. Biſhops and Paſtours are, as Aqueduces and Limbecks, through which the vivifying waters of Chriſts holy Doctrine are derived into our eares, and diſtilled into our ſoules, ſo are not private men: ſhould they be at any time clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and in obſcurity Chriſt would be worſe than his word, his Doctrine fall ſhort, and not come home to us.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It will be ſaid, viſibility is a badge private men wear as well as Biſhops and Doctours; therefore it cannot be inferred more of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151629:55"/>one than of the other. <hi>Repl.</hi> Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility is not peculiar to Biſhop and Paſtours, but neceſſity of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility is; private men in this way of viſibility, being onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingently viſible: So that though this inference be not right, they are viſible men, therefore they are Biſhops and Raſtours; no more than that there are white fowle, therefore they are ſwans, white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs belonging as well to Geeſe, Ducks Pigeons &amp;c. Yet there are Biſhops and Paſtours, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are viſible, holds good; as there are ſwans, therefore they are white fowl; in aſmuch as viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility agreeth neceſſarily to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtours, as whiteneſs doth to ſwans.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It will be ſaid, Divers Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtours have been, whoſe names are not extant;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151629:55"/>therefore Biſhops and Paſtours have no ſtricter relation to viſibility than private men; <hi>Repl.</hi> Biſhops and Paſtours are neceſſarily viſible, either indeterminately, or determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately: indeterminately all; for ſome are neceſſary to make a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church; determinately ſo many, without which there could not be a ſufficient number to make a true viſible Church: Even as Ships in reſpect of paſſing the Sea, all are neceſſary either indeterminately or determinately; indeterminately all, ſome being neceſſary to paſs with, determinately ſo many, without which the Sea is not to be paſſed. Wherefore as the Antecedent is true, the Sequell is falſe; Biſhops and Paſtours having either indeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minately or determinately a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Reference to this ſort of viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; private men onely an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall.</p>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:151629:56"/>
                  <p n="4">4 It will be ſaid, Biſhops and Paſtours are neceſſarily viſible, whil'ſt they live; dead, that neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ceaſeth; <hi>Repl.</hi> Such a viſibility would be to no purpoſe, it not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding the Church of means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and make good her right in caſe of oppoſition; for the queſtion of lawfulneſs in Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, and of their truth in point of Doctrine, ſoaring as high as Chriſt, commonly be ſatisfied by a ſhewing of equall riſe; which ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth a viſibility reaching from Chriſt to the end of the World as power to the Act. The queſtion of the Churches Right is to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided, not unlike that of two great men, laying claim to a Principality, by vertue of ſome pretended deſcent from a certain Prince, or to that of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> River, whether it hath its of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ring from ſuch a Hill or Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151629:56"/>For as to Evidence, this the ſureſt way will be to derive their Pedigree, and to trace the River up to the Head; ſo to clear that, no means more effectuall, than to take a view of the ages gliding betwixt Chriſt and us. If Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours be found ſucceeding each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without intermiſſion, it is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident they are true and Catholick; if otherwiſe, they may not eſcape the brand of uſurpation and intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Truth of Doctrine is diſcernable much after the ſame manner, If it be found to have no way varied, but to have kept its own from Chriſt and the Apoſtles, doubtleſs it is Orthodox, if not, moſt certainly it is new and falſe. In ſhort, by the good help of this viſibility, the Biſhops and Paſtours of Gods Church, together with his
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151629:57"/>Doctrine, ſhine ſo bright through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all ages ſince Chriſt, that who will open their eyes to ſee, and their mouthes to ask, may with eaſe finde whom to obey, and what to believe; for want of this viſibility, Sectaries, boaſt they never ſo much of Antiquity, prove but of late creation, and their Doctrines fond deviſes of unſetled and wavering mindes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <p>The laſt ſhape is, That Church is true and Catholick, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth the Apoſtles Doctrine, clearly delivered in Scripture; but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants Church doth this, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:151629:57"/>
                  <head>ANSWER.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. TRue Doctrine is no mark of a true Church, it being to be ſeen among Schiſmaticks, who for want of Communion are not able to make a true Church; Beſides Doctrine is as divers, as there are divers ſeeming Churches, and ſo not affording any determinate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion drawes in oppoſition of a mark of truth; to which adde that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſuppoſeth Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours, as the means whereby it is conveyed unto us; For Doctrine comes not in the ayre, or by infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but by preaching and teaching of men, not only ſent inwardly by inſpiration, but likewiſe outwardly by ordination or impoſition of hands, of ſuch as have power, as the Prieſts in the old Law, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151629:58"/>and their ſucceſſors in the new were <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. <hi>Levit.</hi> 8. <hi>Math.</hi> 28. therefore it importeth as much to name Biſhops and Paſtours be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore way be given to the mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Doctrine as it is neceſſary paſſing from one extreame to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; to touch firſt the middle. It is no leſs untrue that Proteſtants maintain the Apoſtles Doctrine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in Scripture, inasmuch as they cleave to a ſenſe which the words neither do, nor can beare without wreſting &amp; forcing, as D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Smith</hi> (late Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon</hi>) hath clearly ſhewn in his Collation; to which I muſt remit you for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyding of tedious quotations, as oppoſite to my profeſſed brevity.</p>
                  <p>To be of the Apoſtle, belief, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a full and entire admiſſion of what they believed; For if belief of ſome points only were enough
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151629:58"/>to make two of one belief; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks and Proteſtants, Turks and Jews might crack of unity in Religion, becauſe though they differ in ſome points, yet in other ſome they conſent and agree. Now Heaven being a reward only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and promiſed where there is a full performance of Duty; belief of part of the Apoſtle Belief is as ineffectuall to Salvation as perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance for a time; which moved S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Athan</hi> to ſay that he that did not hold the Catholick Faith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely ſhould for ever periſh: And it is agreeable to reaſon, in regard puniſhment is the reward of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt offered to Gods Majeſtie, which may be done as by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing any one Commandment, ſo by disbelieving any one point; Gods Majeſty ſhining no leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendently in his veracity than in is Will.</p>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151629:59"/>
                  <p>It will be ſaid <hi>Proteſtants</hi> agree with the Apoſtles in ſundamentalls, which is ſufficient to be of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles</hi> belief, and to Salvation; <hi>Repl.</hi> There are two ſortes of Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalls anſwerable to the two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold precept of belief, affirmative; <hi>He that believes ſhall be ſaved;</hi> and negative, <hi>He that doth not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſhall be condemned, Mar.</hi> 16. The firſt ſort is points to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, explicitly or in particular. as the <hi>Trinity,</hi> the <hi>Incarnation, &amp;c.</hi> The ſecond ſort is points to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, at leaſtwiſe, implicitly or in generall, as all points whatſoever relating to belief, both are Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentalls, becauſe both are neceſſary to Salvation, and both are neceſſary to Salvation, becauſe both are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually grounded upon Revelation, whence ariſeth the neceſſitie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of belief; Now admit it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151629:59"/>ſhould be granted that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> agree with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the firſt ſort of Fundamentalls, that is in points neceſſarie to be believed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly, according to the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive precept of belief (which may well be a queſtion, they not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving them upon account of the Church, but for fancie or ſome other humane reſpect) yet diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in the ſecond ſort, that is, in points neceſſarie to be believed, at leaſtwiſe implicitly, according to the negative precept of belief: How is it true that they do not diſagree from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls? It will be ſaid thoſe points, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> diſagree in, were not revealed to the <hi>Apoſtles, Repl.</hi> It is manifeſt they were, there being the ſame light for the revelation of them, as there is for the revelation of the other; to wit, the Churches
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151629:60"/>Tradition, which giving a like exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of both, ought not to be deemed leſs ſufficient for the latter than the former. It will be ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Scripture</hi> had being, the power and right of declaring <hi>Revelation</hi> belonged to the <hi>Church,</hi> but ſince they were tranſferred and given to <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſo as now Gods <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is to be known thence without recourſe to the <hi>Church, Repl.</hi> The power and right of declaring Gods <hi>Revelation</hi> were beſtowed upon the Church, not for the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time only, but for all the time after, for the Commiſſion was not, <hi>each ſame, but all Nations, Mat.</hi> 6. which is not to be accompliſht till the end of the World, when the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be gather'd from their diſperſion, and conſequently imparts the fulneſs of him, that is to ſay, ſo long as this World
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151629:60"/>laſteth, or there is time in being: It will be ſaid, to what purpoſe then did the Evangeliſts ſet pen to paper? <hi>Repl.</hi> For more comfort to give Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the Church and her ſincerity in teaching, and not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one to be his own carver and interpreter. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> is poſitive, <hi>let men eſteem of us, &amp;c. as the diſpencers of Gods myſteries.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. It was ever held an effect of great improvidence, and an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of much confuſion for the people in any ſtate or Common-Wealth, to have the freedome and liberty of conſtruing the Law; Therefore wiſe Lawmakers, to ſhew their care and foreſight for the good and weal publick, as they cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then Laws to be written, ſo did they appoint certain ſelect per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of great abilitie and in egritie, to adminiſter and diſpenſe the ſame.</p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:151629:61"/>
                  <p>This being true, what an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valueing muſt it be of Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and providence, to think that in a Commonwealth of his own im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate eſtabliſhing, as the Church is, he hath left to all indifferently, a liberty to make what ſenſe they pleaſe of his Law, on which, as on a ſhelf or Rock, her peace and ſafety would be in perpetuall danger of Wrack; The Jarres and Garboyles of <hi>Sectaries</hi> having ſcarce had any other ſource than the priviledge every of them took of reading and interpreting <hi>Scripture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Reaſon is clear, becauſe all men are not apt to underſtand alike; for being for the moſt part of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent tempers and compoſures, they have various fancies, which of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity will beget a diverſity of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: Let twenty read and reaſon upon Scripture, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:151629:61"/>to ſome former expoſition, and I dare be bold to ſay, that no two of them ſhall agree; Experience is my warrant in <hi>Luther, Zuing lius, Calvin,</hi> who for all their reading and reaſoning, made no leſs than three contrary and repugnant ſenſes of thoſe plain words; <hi>This is my Body, This is my Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. It will be ſaid, thoſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected perſons, intruſted with the adminiſtring and diſpenſing of the Laws, utter by mouth what they underſtand, and they underſtand no more than what their private reading and reaſoning are able to inform them, ſo that even this way man would be to ſeek; <hi>Repl.</hi> Judges have not only their reading and reaſoning to inform and direct them, but likewiſe the practiſe of former Courts from the very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the Law; at which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151629:62"/>time the ſenſe and meaning of the ſame was declared by the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers themſelves. The Church, beſides the letter of Scripture (which ſhe reads aſſiduouſly, with watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faſting, and prayer, for a right and happy underſtanding thereof) and her own reaſoning, hath the help of a better and ſurer traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt. Now I leave it to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Reader to judge, whether is more like to informe right and ſure of Gods revealed tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he that hath-onely his own private reading and reaſoning to help him, or ſhe, that over and above all theſe, is favoured both by infallible Tradition, and the Holy Ghoſt: And again, whether in a matter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Salvation, it be not an act of imprudence and folly, to believe him rather than her.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:151629:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 16.</hi> Of the Roman Church.</head>
               <p>BY the word Roman are not onely comprized the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of that particular Territory of Rome, but likewiſe all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the world, that acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Biſhops of Rome for their cheif Paſtour, appointed by Chriſt to govern his flock. My taske in this Chapter is to prove, that this company, together with the ſaid Biſhop, compoſe and make up the true Catholique Church.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1</head>
                  <p n="1">1. My firſt proof is, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Chriſtians compoſe, and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151629:63"/>make up the true Catholique Church, to which the definition of the true Catholique Church doth agree; But the difinition of the true Catholique Church doth agree to the above mentioned company, therefore they compoſe and make up the true Catholique Church. The firſt Propoſition is evident, every thing being really one and the ſame with its defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as Man with rationall, Beaſt with irrationall. The ſecond Propoſition I ſhew. The definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the true Catholique Church is, a ſociety of men linck't toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the profeſſion of one Faith, in the uſe of the ſame Sacraments, and under the government of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Paſtours</hi> lawfully ſent, that are able to ſhew their perſonall and doctrinall ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Chriſt and his Apoſtles,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151629:63"/>without the leaſt interruption. A ſociety of men. <hi>And he gave ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and other ſome Evangeliſts, others Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours and Doctours, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmmation of the ſaints, unto the work of Miniſtery, unto the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the body of Chriſt,</hi> linck't together, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. <hi>One body, one ſpirit, one faith, one Baptiſme, ibid:</hi> Lawfully ſent. <hi>No man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the honour to himſelf, but he that is called, as Aaron of God. Heb.</hi> 5. <hi>How ſhall they preach unleſs they be ſent. Rom.</hi> 10. That are able to ſhew &amp;c. The <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of the houſe of our Lord ſhall be prepared in the top of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and all nations, ſhall flow unto it. Jſa.</hi> 2. <hi>He hath placed his Tabernacle in the ſunne. Pſal.</hi> 118. Their Perſonall and doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſucceſſion. <hi>He gave ſome
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151629:64"/>Doctours and Paſtours, &amp;c. Untill wee all meet in the unity of faith. Epheſ.</hi> 4. without the leaſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption. <hi>Behold J am with you alwaies unto the end of the world. Ma.</hi> 6.28.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Let us look upon this defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its ſeverall parts and veiw, if any be diſcrepant from the a forenamed company. The firſt is, <hi>a ſociety of men,</hi> this agreeth to the ſaid company, for in that company is to be ſeen. <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem deſcended from above, Apoc.</hi> 4. A goodly Hierarchy or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly order, and ſubordination of Subdeacon to Deacon; of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con to Prieſt; of Prieſt to Biſhop; of Biſhop to chief Biſhop or Pope, and of the Laity to all: And which is yet more admirable, theſe degrees are ſo maſterlike ſet, that they doe not hinder and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151629:64"/>trouble, but as great &amp; leſs ſtrings muſically tuned, make and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Melodious Harmony of Peace and Concord. The ſecond part is <hi>linck'd together.</hi> This agreeth to the ſaid Company; for in that company there is no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of belief; but one (as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch) ſwayeth, in <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa,</hi> and <hi>America,</hi> where one and the ſame belief is embraced for one and the ſame motive, Gods Revelation propoſed by the Church. The third part is, <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſent.</hi> This agreeth to the ſaid Company; for in that company, <hi>No man clarifieth himſelf,</hi> but one receiveth power from another; the Subdeacon, Deacon, &amp; Prieſt from the Biſhop, the Biſhop from the cheif Biſhop or Pope. The fourth part is <hi>Able to ſhew &amp;c.</hi> This a greeth to the ſaid Company:
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151629:65"/>for in that company an exact ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of power and doctrine is faithfully and with clearneſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; Writers of ſeverall ages and Nations having put forth and publiſhed to the view of the world authentick ſchemes &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogues of Popes,<note place="margin">Coccius, Gual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius.</note> Biſhops &amp; Paſtours ſucceding each other from Chriſt and the Apoſtles, and from time to time layd open their Doctrine. The fifth part is, <hi>without the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption.</hi> And this agreeth with the ſaid Company; for in that Company a Continual pure ſtream of power and Doctrine is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by the ſaid writers, to have been ever ſweetly gliding from its head, Chriſt, and in its proper Channell, Biſhops and Paſtours; and not any moment of time can
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151629:65"/>be pointed at, in which its courſe was ſtopped from beating down infidelity, and imbalming true Belieuers with the fragrant odours of vertve and Religion.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. The ſecond Proof is, that Company compoſeth and maketh up the true <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> which doth acknowledg and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace a power generally claimed, and Doctrine generally profeſſed, by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and Chriſtians ever ſince. But the ſaid Company acknowledgeth and embraceth a power generally claymed and a Doctrine generally profeſſed by the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and Chriſtians ever ſince; Therefore that compoſeth and maketh up the true <hi>Catholick Church.</hi> The firſt Propoſition is
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151629:66"/>undeniable, in aſmuch as Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall power and Doctrine, (where communion is not wanting) are ſure Evidences of the true <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond Propoſition I ſhall ſufficiently clear, by inſtancing the beginning and after-riſing of thoſe Tenets which <hi>Sectaries</hi> hold againſt <hi>Catholicks,</hi> by ſhe wing how the learned of <hi>Catholicks</hi> (who were as the mouth &amp; pen of the reſt) oppoſed the ſaid Tenets, as new and never heard of before: laſtly by producing Councells, witneſſing and confirming, the Orthodoxneſs of this mouth and pen, and branding the contrary for hereſies; Now forasmuch as it is eaſier, to evidence our Fathers acts, than our Grandfathers or great Grandfathers &amp;c, I reſolve to take this way, making my firſt
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:151629:66"/>inſtance in the laſt, &amp; ſo upwards to the Apoſtles. When <hi>Calvin.</hi> 1534. changed the Hierarchie of the Church into Presbyterie, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a ſpirituall preſence of <hi>Chriſts body</hi> in the <hi>Euchariſts,</hi> eſtabliſht a perpetuity in the Poſſeſſion of Grace, deſtroyed all poſſibility of keeping the Commandments, Chriſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, that their Commiſſion was to inculcate that the Government of the Church was inſtituted by <hi>Chriſt Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall,</hi> and not to be altered, that Chriſts preſence in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> was corporall, that grace once had might be loſt by ſinne, that keeping of the Commandments was the way to Salvation, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as poſſible as ſalvation its ſelf. <hi>Staphilus, Lindanus, Hoſius, Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, de Xaintes. Morus, conc:
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151629:67"/>Trident.</hi> when <hi>Zuinglius.</hi> 1525. ſet up a ſigne and figure in the place of Chriſts body, Chriſtians generally profeſſed, as the ſaid Company doth that their Commiſſion was to inculcate that the Body of Chriſt was truly and really in the <hi>Euchariſt, Lindanus. Fleidan. Luth. conc. Trid.</hi> When <hi>Luther.</hi> 1517 reviled the Pope calling him Antichriſt, impugned the Authority of Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, Grace from the Sacraments, Maſs, taught impanature, ubiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſts Body. Chriſtians generally profeſſed, as the ſaid Company doth, that their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was to inculcate that the Pope was Chriſts Vicar appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Rule his flock, That Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells in their Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call decrees were to be obeyed, That the Sacraments did confer
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151629:67"/>grace to all that received them worthily, that Maſs was an holy ſacrifice inſtituted by Chriſt, for a Commemoration of his Death and Paſſion, for exhibition of ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign honour to his Eternall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for propitiation to the living and dead. That ubiquity was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the Godhead, <hi>Echius, Coch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus, Alphonſus Acaſtro, Fiſherus,</hi> the vniverſality of <hi>Collen, Louen, Paris, Henrie the</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. <hi>Conc. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> When <hi>Valdeſius</hi> 1170 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed againſt <hi>Indulgences</hi> and <hi>Purgatory,</hi> Chriſtians generally profeſſed, as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to inculcate that the Catholique Church had power to forgive, not onely the fault or guilt of ſinne, but likewiſe the pain and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due for the ſame: That out of this world there was a place
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151629:68"/>of ſatisfaction for ſuch as departed in grace. <hi>Antoninus, Claudius, Coſſiodus, Conc. Florent. Trident.</hi> When <hi>Photius,</hi> with other greekes 1049 oppoſed the Popes ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, Chriſtians generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate, That the Pope was the ſupream Biſhop and head of the Church. <hi>Rabanus, Haym, Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus, Conc. Florent. Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi> 8 When <hi>Berengarius</hi> 104. grew to that impudence as to out Chriſt quite the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to inculcate, That Chriſts Body was truely and realy there, <hi>Lanfranc, Guitmundus: Blondus, Conc. Lugdunenſe;</hi> When <hi>Albanenſes</hi> 796. queſtioned ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme unction, Chriſtiás generally
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151629:68"/>profeſſed as the ſaid Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doth, That their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was to inculcate, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme unction was one of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Sacraments inſtituted by Chriſt. <hi>Bede, Conc. Worm.</hi> When <hi>Jacobus,</hi> 584 took away Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, Chriſtians generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed as the ſaid Company doth; That their Commiſſion was to inculcate, that Confeſſion of ſinns to a Preiſt rightly impowered was availeable and neceſſary, <hi>Saint Gregory, Caſſiodorus, Conc. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> When <hi>Sonaras</hi> 495 deſpiſed Images, Chriſtians generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed as the ſaid Company doth, that their Commiſſion was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate, that as to other things relating to God, and his ſaints, ſo alſo to Images a certain degree of reſpect and reverence was due. <hi>Saint Hier. Theodor, Conc.</hi> 2.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151629:69"/>
                     <hi>Nic.</hi> When <hi>Vigilantius.</hi> 424. cried down holy Reliques and prayer to Saints, Chriſtians gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, that their Commiſſion was to inculcate, that reſpect to holy things and prayer to Saints was both laudable and beneficiall. <hi>Saint Epiphan. Saint Aug. Saint Hier. Saint Greg. Niſs. Conc. Conſtant. Conc. Laodi.</hi> when <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius.</hi> 405 denied originall ſinne, and the neceſſity of Baptiſme, Chriſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, that ſince the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> all were conceived in originall ſinne, and that to remove it Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was requiſite. <hi>Saint Auguſt. Saint Gregory Naz. Niſſe. Saint Baſil, Theodoret, Saint Ambr. Saint Hier. Saint John, Conc.
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151629:69"/>Milev.</hi> When <hi>Jovinian.</hi> 395 made ſinns all alike greivous, had the ſame eſteem of Marriage and virginity, Chriſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, that their Commiſſion was to inculcate, That ſinns accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their more or leſs repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy to reaſon, were greater ſome than other, that how be it Marriage was good and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet that virginity was better, and to be preferred. <hi>Saint Hier. Saint Auguſt. Conc. Tolenſ.</hi> When <hi>Arius.</hi> 364 deprived the Dead of the livings prayers. Chriſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to inculcate, that to pray for the dead was an act of Piety and mercy. <hi>Saint Auguſt. Saint Ambr. Saint Hier. Saint Chryſ. Saint Epiphan. Conc.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151629:70"/>Conſtant.</hi> 3, <hi>Conc. Nic.</hi> 2. When <hi>Eunomius.</hi> 358. attributed to Faith ſtrength and vertue to keep off the harm of ſin from the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; Chriſtians generally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate; That Chriſtians in ſinne were (notwithſtanding their faith) in ſtate of Damnation. <hi>Saint Baſil. Saint Ephrem. Saint Chryſo.</hi> When <hi>Novatus.</hi> 250. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed admiſſion to the Penitent after Baptiſme conſtituted a Church of meer juſt, Chriſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion was to inculcate that a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner truly repentant was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at any time, and that the Church Militant was not without mixture of bad. <hi>Saint Cypr. Saint Ephrem. Saint Hier. Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151629:70"/>Conc. Rom.</hi> When <hi>Gnoſtici</hi> 129 fancied a Juſtice extrinſecate and imputative, Chriſtians gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally profeſſed, as the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany doth, that their Commiſſion was to inculcate, That juſtice was inherent to the ſoul, and that it conſiſted of a ſpirituall quality called grace, whoſe property is to expell ſinne, to enlighten the minde, to incline and enable the Will to all good. <hi>Iren. Iuſtin. Conc. Trident.</hi> When <hi>Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus.</hi> 55 deſtroyed freewill, opened heaven to faith unaccompanied with good workes, blaſphemed God to be the Author of ſinne, Chriſtians generally profeſſed as the ſaid Company doth, That their Commiſſion was to inculcate that through Adams diſobedience, freewill was weakened, and ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined but not loſt; that faith did
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151629:71"/>diſpoſe and help, but without good works that ſhee was too weak to juſtify a ſinfull ſoul, that God did all good things, and for ſinne, that he did no more than ſuffer and permit. <hi>Saint Peter, Saint Paul, Saint Luke, Saint John, Saint Mathew, Saint James, Saint Jude, Act. Saint Dionyſ. Saint Auguſt. Conc. Trid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. This Proof will gather ſtrength by obſerving, that the above named, but few dayes or Months before their oppoſition, held as the reſt of Chriſtians did, in all points with the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany; and that neither they, nor others in their behalf have left to poſterity the leaſt mention of any number of men in being, before their oppoſition, with whom to joyn and ſide, to make good the ſame. Aſſuredly, if any ſuch
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151629:71"/>thing had been, ſo great an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage would not have been paſſed over in ſilence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 The third and laſt Proof is, That Company compoſeth and makethup the Catholique Church, which is acknowledged even by their Adverſaries, to be <hi>Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call;</hi> But the above mentioned Company is acknowledge even by their Adverſaries, to be <hi>Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall:</hi> therefore that Company compoſeth and maketh up the Catholique Church. The firſt Propoſition is evident: for as much as Apoſtolicall in a right and genuin ſenſe, ſinignifyeth to believe as the Apoſtles believed, which is to be Catholique. The ſecond Propoſition appeares no
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151629:72"/>leſs cleer in ſeverall Proteſtan writers, who expreſſely account, that the Apoſtles firſt planted the Chriſtian faith in England; That the ſame was retained by Biſſiops and Paſtours, from the firſt Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to <hi>Saint Auſtin;</hi> That in ſubſtance it differed not, from that which <hi>Saint Auſtin</hi> brought in; That <hi>Saint Auſtin</hi> was by <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> to convert the <hi>Saxons</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to the <hi>Roman faith;</hi> That the <hi>Roman Church</hi> in <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory the greats time,</hi> was the ſame it is at this preſent. See to this purpoſe. <hi>Perkins. Expoſi.</hi> on the <hi>Creed Pag.</hi> 266. <hi>Powell Conſ. pap. rer. pag.</hi> 103. <hi>Stow, How, Speed, Cambden,</hi> and all the Engliſh Chronicles. Now the <hi>Axiom</hi> in Philoſophy, which aſſureth, Two Extreames which
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151629:72"/>are one with a third, to be one amongſt themſelves, will juſtify this form; <hi>Saint Auſtins</hi> Church and Doctrine were Apoſtolicall; <hi>Saint Auſtins</hi> Church and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine were the ſame with the now Roman: Therefore the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church and Doctrine are Apoſtolicall.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:151629:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP: 17.</hi> Of certain Objections made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Roman Church; Anſwered.</head>
               <p>IT is incdent to vain-glorious and haughty men, to ſpurn at Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and to aſperſe ſuperiours with failings: Pride ſets them on, and malice contrives the means as black as their end, which is to ſhake off obedience, to live at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and without controule. The Enemies of the Roman Church have not ſhewn more Pride in con temning her power, than malice in raiſing falſe and ſlanderous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports againſt her good name: As therefore in the former Chapter I
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151629:73"/>have done my endeavour to aſſert her power; ſo will I in this, to clear her fame, and ſhew her innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie mainly clouded, and ſhot at by the enſuing Objections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:151629:74"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt Objection is, The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> teacheth Chriſts Body to be preſent in many places at once, which implyeth contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The meaſure of Gods power is his will, and his will is above the reach of our capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city: Therefore no wonder if God oftentimes doth that we cannot dive into the underſtanding of, it ſufficeth, we know the thing is done and that we do by his word; which being plain and expreſs for the preſence of Chriſts Body in the Sacrament, and conſequently in many places at once, to doubt thereof, is no leſs than to queſtion Gods veracity. As for implicancy ſome labour to convince this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151629:74"/>of, there is none at all; for though a body cannot be locally in two places at once, by reaſon of locall extenſion, which confines it to one, yet this extenſion being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, as it is poſſible to the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent power; it is as eaſie for a Body to be in ſeverall places at once, as for the Deity to be in three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at once, or for the ſoul to be in the Head, the middle, the feete at once: Neither doth Chriſt, calling himſelf a Door, a Vine, &amp;c. <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.15. any way contradict this truth; becauſe in theſe propoſitions, <hi>I am a Dore, a Vine,</hi> two diſtinct things, and of different kinds are affirmed of each other, which according to the literall and proper ſignification of the words, cannot be true; in that <hi>this is my Body,</hi> the ſame i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denticall thing is affirmed of the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151629:75"/>ſame, to wit, the body of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> out of the Sacrament, when the words began to be in the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> when they end, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>trope</hi> or <hi>figure</hi> is as properly true, as this is the ſigne of the croſs, <hi>Tabitha come forth, Acts</hi> 9. Nor yet thoſe other ſayings, <hi>the Fleſh profiteth nothing, my words are Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Jo.</hi> 6. in as much as they were uttered to ſatisfy the <hi>Caphurnaites,</hi> who being a groſſe carnall people apprehended of Chriſts ſaying, <hi>the bread which I will give is my fleſh, my fleſh is truely foode, unleſs ye eate the fleſh of the Son of man, &amp;c. Jo.</hi> 6. that he meant to give his body to be gnawn and torne in pieces, as ordinarie butchers meat, and that he was not of power to give it any other way; that appears by their murmuring, as conceiving
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151629:75"/>horrour at the eating of humane fleſh, this by queſtion they made how can he? In ſatisfaction to the former apprehenſion, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>the fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> that is, whatſoever fleſh given or received as ordinary fleſh, availeth not the ſoule; in ſatisfaction to the latter <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid, <hi>my words are ſpirit,</hi> that is, are able to effect what they ſignifie or expreſs, that this is the meaning of both <hi>Chriſts</hi> anſwers, I ſhew, becauſe <hi>the fleſh profiteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> literally taken is a falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>Chriſts,</hi> fleſh being no leſs profitable for mans redemption, than ordinary fleſh for his corporall nouriſhment, and my words are Spirit, underſtood otherwiſe would not have been to the Capharnaites queſtion, which, as I, ſaid before, was of his power. Now this meaning
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151629:76"/>is to farre from overthrowing the myſterie of the <hi>realpreſence,</hi> that it clearly confirmes and eſtabliſheth the ſame, for although the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Chriſt</hi> giving his bodie be Spirituall, yet is it not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the reality of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, he was really preſent to the water of Bethſaida <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</hi> 6. Notwithſtanding the manner of his walking was altogether mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous and Spirituall. <hi>Saint Paul.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. knew this conſiſtent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, when after inſtruction of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and worthy receiving, he ſcrupuled not to pronounce con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon the unworthy receiver, not of bread and wine, but the very bodie <hi>of our Lord.</hi> Had <hi>Saint Paul</hi> meant of figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or ſpiritual preſence, he would have ſaid for <hi>not diſcerning the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151629:76"/>figure of the body of our Lord,</hi> and not the <hi>body of our Lord.</hi> Beſides figurative, or ſpirituall preſence are ordinary effects, and within the compaſs of mans power, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore required not any ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary munificency, as Chriſt uſed of his.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If it be true as Philoſophy teacheth, that a conſequence from being, to may bee, is valid and good, Experience demonſtrates, that God hath power to make Chriſts Body really preſent in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places at once; for as much as the ſelf ſame time, he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent with his father in heaven, he appeared and diſcourſed with <hi>Saint Paul</hi> on Earth ſaying, <hi>Saul, Saul, why doſt thou perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute mee? Acts.</hi> 9. For when Saint <hi>Paul</hi> replyed, <hi>who art thou
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151629:77"/>Lord?</hi> Hee anſwered, I am <hi>Jeſus whom thou doſt perſecute.</hi> Even in nature there is a Reſemblance and light of this Myſtery: one and the ſame water is in the Fountain, River and Lake at once, one and the ſame voyce in Thouſands of Eares at once; one and the ſame face in ſundry looking glaſſes at once; ſhould we believe onely that which we underſtand, there would not be any beleif in us of Myſteries of faith; they being all above the reach of humane Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It will be oppoſed, Although God by his omnipotent Power, can make the Body of Chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, in many places at once, yet his pleaſure is not to do it, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſtrange irreverences, and abſurdities which would enſue
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151629:77"/>thereof, as to be ſubject to the eating and tearing in peices of Doggs, Catts, Mice, and to the abuſe of wicked men and Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants. <hi>Reply.</hi> He that is of power to render a Body really preſent in ſeverall places at once, without doubt is able to defend, and keep the ſame from all outrages; as God is pleaſed to do in this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, by removing locall extenſion, and by conſequence poſſibility, by meanes whereof, Doggs, Catts, and Mice, can onely tear and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the accidents of Bread and wine: wicked men and Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants offer violence to the ſame, but not hurt or annoy the Body of Chriſt; no more than he were of force to wrong the Godhead, that ſurprized with a raging fit, ſhould ſtrike at the ayre, with an
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151629:78"/>intention to do him miſcheif. But admit theſe pretended incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences ſhould follow, I do not conceive there could be inferred any other than a continuation of that ardent love of Chriſt, which he ſhewed to man, when he eſtranged himſelf from his eternall father, to bear with patience and mildneſs, hunger, cold, whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings, ſpittings, thorns; and laſt of all the bitter and diſgracefull Death of the Croſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:151629:78"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>The ſecond objection is: the <hi>Roman Church</hi> believes <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> 2 doctrine unheard of till the Councell of <hi>Lateran. Anſwer</hi> the name <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> was indeed impoſed by the Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> called the Great, as the name <hi>Conſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> by the firſt Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> and the name <hi>Trinity</hi> by the Church, but as the things ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the names <hi>Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall</hi> and <hi>Trinity</hi> were generally believed before the impoſitions of thoſe names, ſo the thing ſignified by the name <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> was generally believed before this name was thought of, witneſs <hi>Saint Cyrill, Jeruſo. Catecheſi
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151629:79"/>myſtag.</hi> 4. ſaying of <hi>Chriſt he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned water into wine in Cana of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile &amp; ſhall we not believe him that he hath turned wine into his bloud? Saint Ambroſe</hi> ſayes to the ſame effect, <hi>L.</hi> 4. <hi>de ſacram. C.</hi> 4. <hi>before the words of conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it is bread, after conſecration, of bread is made the fleſh of Chriſt &amp;c. If the words of our Lord Jeſus be ſo powerfull to give being to that was not, how much more are they able</hi> to turn one thing <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another?</hi> The very words of conſecration, <hi>this is my body</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm no leſs, in as much as being an operative propoſition, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not, as a ſpeculative propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth, but maketh the thing it fignifies, which implyeth a reall change either of Chriſts body into bread, or of bread into Chriſts
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151629:79"/>body; for how can bread remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bread be Chriſts body? Or Chriſts body continuing the ſame be bread? Surely no more than water, while it is water, can be wine, or a ſtone, ſo long as it is a ſtone, can be a tree. Now that the change is not of Chriſts body into bread is evident, becauſe then Chriſt ſhould have ſaid this is bread, but ſaying <hi>this is my body,</hi> demonſtrates clearly that the change is of bread into Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which is fitly named <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> as declaring the nature of the myſtery believed. It will be oppoſed that <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> is, againſt experience, which ſhewes that conſecrated bread and wine nouriſh. <hi>Repl.</hi> if any ſuch triall hath been made, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the nouriſhment was
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151629:80"/>ſupernaturall, God ſupplying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his extraordinary power the war of the ſeverall ſubſtances of brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and wine to the end to ſave faith which according to <hi>Saint Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Hebr.</hi> 11. is of things not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. It will be oppoſed that after conſecration ſtill remain the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of bread and wine, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſſence conſiſts in inhering in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. <hi>Repl.</hi> As it is true tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> after conſecration the accidents o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bread and wine continue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſame, ſo its falſe that their eſſence conſiſts in inherence; for the defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of accident is apt to inhere, which may be without inherence by meanes of Gods Omnipotency, whereto their is a neceſſity to have recourſe in all matters of faith, nature being in thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at a loſs and uſeleſs, as <hi>Saint
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151629:80"/>Hilar. Lib.</hi> 8 <hi>de Trinitate</hi> well obſerveth; his words are, <hi>In Gods matters wee are not to ſpeak after the ordinary manner of men.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:151629:81"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>3.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The third objection is; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Roman Church committeth Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latry in her adoration at Maſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bowing to the name of Ieſus Altars, Images, and Reliques Anſwer. By the Commandment <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelf any graven thing, nor adore it, Exod</hi> 20. is neither forbid the art of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graving, Carving, Printing, Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Caſting, Sowing, Embroyder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; nor yet all manner of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous honor to be given to Creatures: For in the old Taſtament (where this Commandement is enjoyned) the uſe of thoſe ſeverall acts was held lawfull, and Religious ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour exhibited to the fiery Buſh by <hi>Moyſes, Exod.</hi> 25. to the
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151629:81"/>Oracle by the High Preiſts, 3. <hi>Kings.</hi> 27. and to the Arke by <hi>David, Exod.</hi> 3. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 131. And God himſelf juſtified them therein, by ſtriking <hi>Vzziah</hi> with Leproſie, and <hi>Oza.</hi> with death, for not forbearing to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, with holy and ſacred things without authority. 2. <hi>Paral.</hi> 26. <hi>Kings.</hi> 6 ſo that all this Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement forbids, is to make graven things, to the end to honour them with divine honour, that is, to make Gods of them, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans did.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now to vindicate the Roman Church from all Idolatry in her worſhip, it is to be noted, That all things are not of equall worth, but that ſome things ſurpaſſing other ſome in perfection and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, are more worthy than
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151629:82"/>other; whence it is, that God is ſuperiour to all things, Angells to men, and men ſome to others. And hereupon is grounded honour and the degrees thereof, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the variety of perfections and excellencies found in things: for where perfection and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency are diſcovered to be, there the very light of nature teacheth honour to be due more or leſs, as the degrees of excellency and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection are obſerved to bee higher or lower. Now honour (as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to man) is an outward reſpect given to a thing, with an inward act of acknowledgment of ſome perfection and excellency in the ſame. So as to the compleating of honour (as to us) two actions are required; an exteriour of the body, and an interiour of the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151629:82"/>mind; when either is wanting, honour becomes lame and manke. A timorous man apprehending danger in exhibiting outward reſpect where it is due, maketh onely an inward acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this comes ſhort of honour. A man diſtracted or mad, and ſo uncapable of the inward acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, by reaſon of his diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered ſences and faculties, giveth an outward reſpect; this is as far from honour as the other.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Both actions (viz.) both the inward and outward may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed to God, and creatures; as it is lawfull to bow or kneel to God, ſo to creatures, as we may ſee, <hi>Joſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.33. <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Kings.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Paral.</hi> 29. <hi>Jud.</hi> 10.13. <hi>Eſter.</hi> 8. <hi>Num.</hi> 2. Now to diſcerne, when theſe actions
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151629:83"/>come within compaſs of divine religious, and Civil honour, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends wholly on a right, and well differencing of the perfections and excellencies of the things ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured. To bow or kneel to a thing with an inward acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, that its perfections and excellencies are abſolute, unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipated, and infinitely excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all other, is divine honour; to bow or to kneel to a thing with an inward acknowledgment, that its perfections and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies are onely participated, and relative to God, Chriſt, or ſome glorious ſoul, is religious honour; to bow or kneel to a thing with an inward acknowledgment, that its perfections, and excellencies relate to ſome wordly dignity or preheminence, is Civil honour.
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:151629:83"/>Divine honour is proper to God, and unattributable to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture under Idolatry; Neither doth the Church of Rome afford this honour but to God alone; her adoration at Maſs being not meant, nor directed to the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of Bread and Wine, nor to the figures of Hoſt and Chalice next to ſight (for in theſe ſhe doth not acknowledge to be the perfections and Excellencies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to God) but to the perſon of Chriſt hid and covered under the ſaid accidents and figures. She alloweth indeed of religious honour to the name of Ieſus, to Altars, Pictures, Reliques, rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to God, Chriſt, and his Saintes; as ſhe doth of Civil, to things in relation to temporall dignities and preheminencies:
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151629:84"/>But to find fault with this, were to blame juſtice, for giving to every thing its due, in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the truth; it being moſt true and undoubted, that the name of <hi>Jeſus, Altars, Pictures and Reqliques,</hi> bear relation to <hi>God, Chriſt,</hi> and his Saintes, as perſons in dignities, and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies to the ſame.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To urge againſt the Lawfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of adoration at <hi>Maſs,</hi> from the interpoſition of Creatures, would prove too much, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt, were not adorable in Churches, in the fieldes, nay at all, by reaſon of a neceſſity of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of walls, the Heavens, or Chriſts Body betwixt the Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and his ſacred perſon.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It will be oppoſed, Chriſt is not capable of adoration in the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151629:84"/>Sacrament, he not appearing there like himſelf with glory and Majeſty. <hi>Repl.</hi> Chriſt is adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble where, and howſoever he is pleaſed to be; elſe the three Kings, <hi>Saint Mary Magdalen,</hi> and the Apoſtles were reprovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for doing him homage, not in a ſumptuous Palace, and enthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under a rich cloth of State, but in a poor ſtable, a duſty man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, having for Canopy, a rack of hay, not gloriouſly attired, and accompanied with Nobles, but in ſwadling Cloathes betwixt an Ox, and an Aſs, not like a Prince, but a Mechanicke, a Gardener, a Carpenter. The poorneſs and meanneſs of the manner Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in, not onely doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of the duty of adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but renders him much more
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:151629:85"/>adorable; for exaltation is humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities reward, and ſo it is but meet, they go hand in hand, and take increaſe together, that the height of that, may anſwer the depth of this. For which reſpect <hi>Saint Paul</hi> ſticked not to bid ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be given to the very name of <hi>Jeſus, Phil.</hi> 2.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:151629:85"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>4.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The fourth objection is. The Roman Church challengeth pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to forgive ſinns which belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth onely to God. <hi>Anſ.</hi> All Power is naturally &amp; originally in God, as Lord Paramount of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; but not incommunicable: for as he hath beſtowed the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of governing kingdomes and Common-wealths on Kings and Magiſtrates. <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. ſo the Power of remitting of ſinns on the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours: yet men, having theſe powers by way of gift and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation, may not be ſaid to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, or to forgive ſinns, but as Gods ſubſtitutes and Delegates, ſuitably to the Condition of their inferiority and ſubjection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:151629:86"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The fift objection is. The Roman Church derogateth from <hi>Chriſtes</hi> Mediatorſhip, making it common to Saints and Angells. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Things that are like have ſometimes the ſame denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; ſo kings and Judges are called Gods, for ſome reſemblance betwixt Gods power and theirs. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.1, 6. The Roman Church then obſerving in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of Saints and Angells, a certain likeneſs to the Mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, they being both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Charitable and good deſires for others, may not unfitly call them alike by the name of Mediation. But ſhe is ſo farre hereby from intending the leaſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:151629:86"/>prejudice to Chriſts Mediation, either in confounding or equall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame with that of Saints and Angells, that ſhe puts as wide a difference betwixt them, as can be betwixt two things of different appellations; acknowledging in Chriſts Mediation a worth or right, whereto the thing deſired is of Juſtice due; in the mediations of Saints and Angells, onely a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of moving Gods goodneſs and mercy to grant their deſires; which being not held in jurious to Chriſts Mediation to allow of, as good in the prayers of ſinners, hated and abominated by God for their Crimes and iniquities, much leſs ought it to be eſteemed a wrong to attribute it to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion, and prayers of Saints and Angells, whoſe purity and
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:151629:87"/>ſanctity, render them gracious and pleaſing in the ſight of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It will be oppoſed, in the vaſt diſtance as is betwxt heaven and earth, Saints and Angells cannot hear. <hi>Repl.</hi> bleſſed Soules in their ſtate of ſeparation have, as Angells, (<hi>Luke.</hi> 15.) an hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quite other from that of ſoules immerſed and plunged in fleſh and blood: theſe hear by meanes of corporall organs, which limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within a certain diſtance, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not receive impreſſion out of the ſame; Thoſe; hear with their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, which are by ſo much the more open, and quick of apprehenſion, by how much the leſs their dependence is on matter. The Saints then being freed of Corporall Cloggs, may hear at any diſtance.</p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:151629:87"/>
               <p n="3">3. It will be oppoſed, Be it, Saints can hear at what diſtance ſoever; yet this is not poſſible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs objects be propoſed: and what capacity in prayers ſent ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off, as to reach to Heaven? <hi>Repl.</hi> Catholiques boaſt not of any ſuch vertue in their prayers; but they beleive (as is confeſſed by all) that God is every where, in Heaven, on Earth, and all the way betwixt both: and that he is the cheif and principall cauſe of all effects, and ſo of mans prayers. Now it being proper for every cauſe to relate to its effects, and ſo to repreſent the ſame, as look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glaſſes do faces, and other oppoſed objects; the Saints (whoſe happineſs conſiſts in a clear viſion of God) muſt needes ſee and behold (amongſt other
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:151629:88"/>effects of his goodneſs and mercy) the Petitions of thoſe, who become humble ſuitors to them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It will be oppoſed, If Saints and Angells hear not mens pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers before God propoſeth them, he knoweth them beforehand; whence may be inferred, that their interceſſion is needleſs. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Gods foreſight of mens prayers, makes not the interceſſion of Saints and Angells any way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable or fruitleſs; inaſmuch as the effect intended thereby is not to better Gods underſtanding, but to obtain from his bleſſed will, mercy and compaſſion: For which the interceſſion of Saints and Angells is powerfull; as well becauſe it is an act of fervent Charity (the practiſe whereof is moſt pleaſing and acceptable to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151629:88"/>God) as alſo, becauſe Saints and Angells are Gods freinds and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites. Princes have often no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſubjects impriſonments and condemnations, yet ſeldome give reprieves or enlargements, but at the entreaty of ſome freind or favourite. Men are warranted, yea wiſhed to pray for one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. notwithſtanding God hath the foreſight of their wants and neceſſities, <hi>Davids</hi> adultery and guilt of blood were in the ſight of God unpardoned, till after a low humiliation, and an hearty acknowledgment of his fault. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 12.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:151629:89"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>6.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The ſixth Objection is, the Roman Church entertaineth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and Contrariety in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the <hi>Dominicans</hi> maintaining a Phiſicall predetermination; The <hi>Jeſuits</hi> a morall; Thoſe, that the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> was conceived in originall ſinne; theſe, that ſhe was prevented by Grace, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the ſame. And if this be not enough to inferre contrariety in Religion, ſeverall Councells have contradicted each other. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Not every difference but a difference in pointes of faith, makes diviſion and contrariety in Religion: the Dominicans and Jeſuits onely quarell about opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it being no matter of beleif,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:151629:89"/>that Gods predetermination is Phiſicall or Morall, or that the bleſſed Virgin was conceived in originall ſinne, or in grace. Theſe are meer Schoole nicities, and not at all deſtructive to that unity, which Catholiques ſo much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence in Religion. It is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, that generall and approved Councells have contradicted one another in matters of Faith, or Occumenicall decrees: They have indeed talked and diſcourſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, yea, latter Councells have altered and changed Laws and conſtitutions of government made and eſtabliſhed by former. But this onely proves that Councells admit a liberty, and freedome to debate matters of Religion, and that what was once good and convenient, may prove afterwards
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:151629:90"/>(Circumſtances varying) bad and inconvenient, which no wayes prejudices beleif. And this is it, and all <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Auſtïn</hi> hints, where he ſayes, <hi>the precedent generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells are mended by the following. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cont. Donatiſt. Cap.</hi> 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:151629:90"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The ſeventh objection is, the Roman Church is injurious to Chriſts merits, approving of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane merits. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> Reaſon and experience ſhew a diverſity of Agents; That as ſome are neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated as beaſts, other ſome are fee as men, and therefore capable of merit and demerit, whereby they are differenced from beaſts, which are uncapable of either. The Aſſertion then of humane merits, is no other wrong to Chriſt, than the affirming of a plain and clear truth can be wrong to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It will be oppoſed, men are capable of merit and demerit in order to temporall; but not to eternall reward. <hi>Repl.</hi> As God
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:151629:91"/>hath enabled men to deſerve tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, ſo eternall Rewards, as is apparent in Scripture; terming Heaven, <hi>a Crown of Juſtice a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, a Goale,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 9. which neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſe merits as their correla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, bare actions void of deſert, being look'd on, onely as by way of gift. It were indeed no leſs than Blaſphemy, to go about to equall in worth other merits with Chriſts; but the Roman Church offereth not any ſuch thing, whileſt ſhe beleiveth Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to be of infinite value, others onely of finite; Chriſts merits to have their deſert, and worth from no other; others to hold depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for both of them: Rather the Roman Church by aſſerting other merits, and withall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151629:91"/>their deſert and worth to flow from Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, attributeth more to Chriſts merits than they do, who deny other merits. For hereby are yeilded to Chriſts actions a capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of meriting themſelves, and a communicability of the ſame to other actions, which are two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: and to acknowledg two perfections in a thing is undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly to give more to that thing, than to acknowledg onely one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It will be oppoſed, All acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons beſides Chriſts, are dutyes; and dutyes are inconſiſtent with merit. <hi>Repl.</hi> They are ſo without Covenant and acceptance; ſo is obedience in a Childe, a ſervant, a ſubject, due to his father, his maſter, his Prince: Nevertheleſs as a father, a maſter, a Prince ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151629:92"/>a Compact to gratify ſome particular act of his Childe, his ſervant, his ſubject, innables the ſame, and entitles it to what was promiſed; even ſo by the meanes of Gods Covenant (1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.) that he will reward certain actions of men (though otherwiſe due) and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the ſame as worthy, they become meritorious, and a reward due: upon this accompt <hi>Saint Paul</hi> deemed it no preſumption to challenge at the hands of God, a Crown of Juſtice for his good fighting, well running and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant keeping of <hi>Faith.</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:151629:92"/>
               <head>Objection. <hi>8.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. The eighth and laſt objection is, The Roman Church giveth the Communion under one kind, contrary to Chriſts inſtitution. <hi>Anſwer.</hi> There is a great deal of difference betwixt Chriſts inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and his commandements; Theſe requiring both beleife and obſervance, thoſe onely beleife: For although Chriſts actions be good examples for us to imitate, yet, as ſuch, they impoſe not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation upon imitation. Chriſt faſted forty dayes, and as many nights, went into the Deſart to be tempted, forbare Mariage, &amp;c. are all bound to do the like? none will ſay it: The common practiſe of all religions to the contrary cries
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:151629:93"/>no; wherefore the Roman Church beleiving Chriſts inſtitution of the Sacrament to have been under both kindes, giveth to it its full due. for the Communion under one, there being no Commandement forbidding the ſame; it is raſhneſs in a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and want of charity to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne her as Sacriligious for ſo doing.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Theſe words indeed, <hi>do this in Commemoration of me, Drink ye all of this,</hi> imply a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; but concerning onely Preiſtes, to whom as the power of making, ſo the obligation of taking under both kinds, is pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar and proper; thoſe other <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ye eat the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drink his blood,</hi> import a Commandement too, and that
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151629:93"/>extending to the <hi>Laity;</hi> but fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the things, that is to ſay, upon the body and blood of Chriſt, and not upon the kindes, leaves them indifferent and free. The reaſon of both is, becauſe by this Commandement, Chriſts maine drift is (as the words plainely intimate) to inforce a Spirituall food; which being Chriſt, Body and Blood, and ſince his Reſurrection grown inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, may indifferently be taken under one or both kindes: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by that (as the words like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe clearly beare) he cheifely aymes at a Remembrance of his death and Paſſion; which inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a ſeparation of his Soule from his Body, and his Blood from his fleſh cannot be ſo live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and fully repreſented under
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:151629:94"/>one kind. For Confirmation, looke up into the Primitive times, even of the Apoſtles and Chriſt. <hi>Acts.</hi> 2.42, 46. and you will find by their promiſcuous Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, ſometimes under one kind, ſometimes under another, and ſometimes under both, that they never underſtood of any Commandement of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating under both kinds.</p>
               <p>And thus have you layed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you the will of God, to which all that believe a God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a conformity to be due. Now although I am ſatisfied by what hath been ſaid, that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Roman Catholiques have this Conformity, yet I may not aſsure my ſelfe that others will be ſo; knowing full well, that the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt reaſoning is but beating the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151629:94"/>ayre without Gods grace, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it concerns all to crave it. The way to obtain it is to love one another, and the way to this, is to keep newtrality in our Wills, for if our wills be once admitted to ſide with our Iudgments; Anger, Hatred, and other paſſions will crowd in, and they being ſworn diſturbers of peace, will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly break Unity, which is the bond and tie of love. If our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will needes jarre and quarrell, let them fight it out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, having worried each other they will at lengh be glad to give over and reſt; by meanes whereof, we ſhall be in a faire likelyhood of becoming one ſheep-fold: And then Chriſt will own us all as our Common Paſtour, and guide to Eternity, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
